<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Meanes to prevent perishing. Or, The usefulnesse of the saving knowledge of God. Discovered in these particulars; I. The blessed tendency the knowledg of God hath to bring men to salvation. II. The one-ness of the Father, Son, and Spirit. III. The excellency of Christs person. IV. The excellent nature of eternal life. By W.S. a servant of the Lord Jesus.</title>
            <author>W. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E955_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207616</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866657</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866657</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118935</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92710)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118935)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 142:E955[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Meanes to prevent perishing. Or, The usefulnesse of the saving knowledge of God. Discovered in these particulars; I. The blessed tendency the knowledg of God hath to bring men to salvation. II. The one-ness of the Father, Son, and Spirit. III. The excellency of Christs person. IV. The excellent nature of eternal life. By W.S. a servant of the Lord Jesus.</title>
                  <author>W. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 66, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and are to be sold by Fr. Smith, in Flying-Horse Court in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Signes of a dying Christian" on final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 10".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Knowableness --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118935:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MEANES TO PREVENT PERISHING OR, THE USEFULNESSE OF The Saving Knowledge OF GOD.</p>
            <p>Diſcovered in theſe Particulars;
<list>
                  <item>I. The bleſſed tendency the Knowledg of God hath to bring Men to Salvation.</item>
                  <item>II. The One-neſs of the Father, Son, and Spirit.</item>
                  <item>III. The excellency of Chriſts Perſon.</item>
                  <item>IV. The excellent nature of Eternal Life.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W</hi> S. a Servant of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſ. 4.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>My people are deſtroyed for lack of Knowledge.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Fr. Smith,</hi> in Flying-Horſe Court in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118935:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118935:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe following lines are brought to thy view through the deſire of ſome that heard them Preached, and could not be ſatisfied till others had a taſte of them as well as themſelves. It grieves me for thy ſake that a ſubject of this worth hath not been brought forth by ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abilities; but ſeeing it is my lot to be the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of its birth; I muſt preſent a few requeſts to thee. And the firſt is this: that thou wouldſt conſider the uſefulneſs of theſe moſt precious truths, how much they will contribute toward the attainment of thine eternal peace. Knowledge in general is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of all her Sons to be of excellent worth; but amongſt all Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the knowledg of God in Jeſus Chriſt muſt be confeſs'd to be a jewel of the choiceſt worth, it is the Corner Stone of all Religion and piety that tends to ſet thy judgement right in all other points, and an excellent guide to the right interpretation of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; It hath likewiſe a great command over the Conſcience, and hath a bleſſed tendence to keep thee from prophaneneſs, unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and negligence; when once thou comeſt to know God in Chriſt, thou canſt not well through deſpair want incouragement to ſerve God, nor yet through preſumption take the boldneſs to wander from his Commandements; but this Grace is ſuch a help to keep thy heart and life in an upright frame, that without very much wilfulneſs thou canſt not well go out of thy way to happineſs. And likewiſe the knowledge of the worth of Eternal Life tends much to draw thy mind from Eartly vanities to thoſe things that be above. A ſecond deſire I have to thee is this: That thou wilt lay aſide that overlineſs and formality of Spirit wherewith Books of this nature are oftentimes read, as if they were things that concerned us not; but be ſo faithful to thy Souls intereſt, as to read this without
<pb facs="tcp:118935:3"/>prejudice, partiality, and ſlightneſs of ſpirit; lay up theſe truths in thine heart, and bring forth the fruit of them, and doubtleſs they will make thy converſation to ſhine to the praiſe of the Grace of God in this life, and alſo make thee a meet heir of that glorious inheritance prepared for all them that love the appearing of our Lord Jeſus. Thirdly, I beſeech thee if thou meeteſt with Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Comfort, as I truſt thou wilt in the reading of this Book, when thine heart is warm preſent a requeſt to the Throne of Grace for the Author thereof, that he may never be ſo unhappy as to carve all theſe ſweet dainties away to others from himſelf, but that he may be through Grace inabled to take his own ſhare of them for his ſaving advantage. So commending my poor, yet faithful Labours to thy ſerious conſideration, and to the bleſſing of the great God of Heaven and Earth, I remain thine in the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118935:3"/>
            <head>MEANES TO PREVENT PERISHING.</head>
            <div n="1" type="exercise">
               <head>THE FIRST EXERCISE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 17.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true God, and Jeſus Christ whom thou haſt ſent.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the words immediately going before, you may obſerve, that our Lord Jeſus is a ſpeaking by way of acknowledgment unto his Father, of that authority and power that he had given him over all Fleſh. And in particular, to give eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life to a certain number there ſpecified. Which words I ſhall not ſpeak further to now, having opened them the laſt time I ſpake unto you. In the words now read unto you, you are to conſider in what ſence the knowledg of God and of Chriſt is Eternal Life. I ſhall apply my ſelf to this only at this time, and not ſtand to ſhew you what is here meant by <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> having done it ſo lately; nor yet ſtand to ſhew you in what ſence the Father ſent Chriſt, nor what
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118935:4"/>to do; nor wherefore he is ſaid to be the <hi>only true God.</hi> But I ſhall leave all this till another time, and come to this particular only at this time, to conſider, how the knowledg of God and of Chriſt is Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>Firſt, then let us conſider whether the meaning of the words be this, That the perſons that know the Father, and Jeſus Chriſt, do indeed poſſeſs Eternal Life. Or,</p>
               <p>Secondly, Whether they that know God and Chriſt are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by aſſured of Eternal Life. Or,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Whether thoſe that know the Father, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt have thereby a very excellent means, that hath a very gracious tendency in it, to bring the perſons in whom this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg is to Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>Now I ſhall not ſtand to oppoſe the two former Expoſitions, nor undertake to ſay, that in no ſence or degree they might be granted to be true; yet the latter I take to be the meaning of the words, namely this: <hi>That the knowledg of God, and of Jeſus Chriſt is a means of Eternal Life.</hi> Beloved, I pray you obſerve it, when the Scripture ſaith, the <hi>knowledg of God is eternal life:</hi> leſs than this cannot be in it, that it is a means thereof. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray you obſerve this general Concluſion from the words.</p>
               <p>Doct. 1. <hi>That the knowledg of God, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, is a glorious means of Eternal Life, that hath a very gracious tendency in it to bring perſons in whom this knowledg is, to that happy enjoyment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall name you two or three Texts more that ſpeak the ſame language; the firſt is in the 9 of <hi>Ier.</hi> 23, 24. <hi>verſes, Let not the wiſe man glory in his wiſdome nor the mighty in his might; let not the rich man glory in his riches; but let him that gloryeth glory in this, that he underſtandeth and knoweth me.</hi> Mark it beloved, <hi>let not the wiſe man glory in his wiſdom;</hi> and yet wiſdom is a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent gift, that might better be gloried in then riches or ſtrenth, or any gift of that like nature, and yet the ſpirit of God grants no liberty to glory in it; but in this ſaith the Lord, let him glory, <hi>that he underſtandeth, and knoweth me.</hi> Now if in this you may ſo freely glory by the allowance of the Holy Spirit, and yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in gifts nor parts; ſurely this knowledg is of a moſt excellent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118935:4"/>tendency, to bring much advantage and good to the Soul.</p>
               <p>Another text you ſhall find in the 1 of <hi>Cor.</hi> the 1.21. <hi>For after that in the wiſdom of God, the world by wiſdom knew not God; it pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſs of preaching to ſave them that beleeve.</hi> Here you may ſee plainly, not only that preaching ſaves mens ſouls; but alſo what preaching it is that does it. I pray you note it wel, you may ſee the cure that is neceſſary for ſalvation, by the diſeaſe that hinders it, it is very evident the worlds diſeaſe that hinders their ſalvation, is this; they know not God, therefore it muſt be ſuch preaching as makes God known to the ſoul that muſt bring it to beleeving, and ſo to ſalvation.</p>
               <p>I ſhall name you but one text more and that is in the 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7, 8. <hi>When the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from heaven, with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God.</hi> Take notice I pray you, that one of the two great ſins which Chriſt will come to puniſh with everlaſting flames at the great day, is ignorance of God. Now therefore it muſt be removed, and the knowledg of God in the ſtead thereof muſt poſſeſs the Souls of all thoſe that ſhall inherit eternall life. I ſhall give you the reaſon of this truth, and ſo haſten to the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>Now the reaſon is moſt evident, if you look Heb. 11.6. <hi>For without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe him; for he that cometh to God, muſt beleeve he is.</hi> Here you ſee faith in God is of abſolute neceſſity to the pleaſing of him; But no man in the world can beleeve further then he hath ground to know the truth of that he beleeveth: as it is written, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14. <hi>How ſhall they beleeve in him of whom they have not heard?</hi> The anſwer muſt be they cannot; for ſo much the queſtion intends. So that without hearing, or ſome means to know the Lord, it is impoſſible to come to beleeving. I ſhall now come to open this point unto you, and to ſhew you in what particulars, the knowledg of God, and of Chriſt, is of ſuch uſe, and help to you in point of beleeving, and ſo of ſalvation.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, my beloved, a perſon that knows God in his Son, is thereby kept from deſparation, and ſees in God a ground of boldneſſe and incouragement to caſt it ſelf upon his free grace, which one ignorant of God cannot do; <hi>But he that knows his name will truſt in him,</hi> Pſal. 9.10. how low ſoever a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is, though he be never ſo unworthy a ſinner, and ſees not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118935:5"/>the leaſt ground of hope in himſelf; it doth not diſcourage him nor keep him from beleeving, but he ſees that in God and in Chriſt, that not only gives him boldneſs, but ſuch a ground of boldneſs and incouragement, that he clearly ſees that if he come in good earneſt now, he ſhall not be caſt off, although he have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been never ſo wicked; and the ground of this confidence is the name of God. You know that in a very great number of places the Lord hath manifeſted himſelf a God of mercy and love, yea a ſin-for-giving God, and a gracious God; but I ſhal name you but one text for this, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6. the Lord there proclaims his own name by which he will be known for ever, <hi>Jehova ſtrong, mercifull, and gracious,</hi> &amp;c. and you muſt know that God is not one thing &amp; his name another; neither is he one and his mind, intentions, and decrees, or deſires, another; but he is unchangeably, &amp; eternally the ſame for ever. Now I pray you conſider it, grace and mercy being not qualities in God, but in him it is nature, and it is his eſſence, and unchangeable Being; and therefore he doth not, nor cannot want mercy for the moſt ungodly, yea the verieſt hypocrite, and enemy he hath in the whole world; and the reaſon wherefore any ſoul miſſeth of mercy, is not through any want of mercy in God; no nor for want of mercy to that ſoul in particular that miſſeth of it; but becauſe it will not ſtand with the glory of his other attributes, in ſome caſes to ſhew mercy; for you muſt know that God can do nothing unworthy of his own glorious Name and Being; and therefore ſuch perſons as will not come to Chriſt, and that chuſe darkneſs rather than light, and turn the grace of God into wantonneſs, and do this wilfully and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately, it doth not ſtand with the wiſdom, juſtice, and Soveraignty of God, to give eternall life to theſe perſons; but if perſons do not wilfully refuſe there own mercies, there is that grace in God which will and doth extend it ſelf whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it can, without diſhonour to his juſtice, and prudence: Now where a perſon knows this, and that which may be known of God, and of Chriſt, that is revealed in the word, and ought to be known; I ſay ſuch a one cannot but ſee ſufficient ground to come to God, and to depend upon him for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
               <p>Nay further, there is no objection whatſoever can be raiſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118935:5"/>by the devill againſt a ſinners coming to Chriſt, but he that knows what may be known of God, and of Chriſt, will have wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to anſwer it; for if the Devill come and ſay, it is true, as great ſinners as thou haſt been, have been pardoned, and ſo might eſt thou too, if that were all, but alaſs thou art an impentient and an unconverted wretch, hardened in thy ſins, there is no hope for thee. Yes ſayes the ſoul, but there is and good hope too through grace, for God is a God of grace and faithfullneſs, and hath not only promiſed eternall life to gracious ſouls, but he hath alſo promiſed grace to ungracious ones, as in <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.22, 23. there converting grace is promiſed to ſcornners if they will yet hearken to God, and many more like promiſes there be. But it may be the Devill will further object and ſay; it is true, indeed God is gracious to invite unconverted ſinners to ſeek him, and hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them mercy, as in <hi>Iſa</hi> 59.6, 7. but alaſs thy caſe is worſe then ſo for thou haſt no mind to ſeek him, but art for ever loſt a very ſlave to ſin, and the very captive of the Devill, taken by him at his will; yea ſaith the ſoul that knows God and Chriſt, Satan thou canſt not well ſay worſe of me then I do deſerve, yet is there good ground for me to go to God for mercy, and to truſt in him alſo, for he hath ſent his Son <hi>to ſeek and to ſave thoſe that be loſt.</hi> And although I cannot yet bring my heart to ſeek him as I ſhould, yet Chriſt is faithfull and will do the work he hath undertaken, and ſeek ſuch loſt ones as I am; and although I am a ſlave and a captive to the Devil. Yet I know Chriſt came to ſet at liberty ſuch captives, yea and I know that whatſoever my ſins have been, or whatever my luſts are for ſtrength, my ſouls diſeaſes cannot be too great for Chriſt to cure; all the ends of the earth, and I although I be the worſt in the company, may look to him and be ſaved; ſaved from ſin as well as from wrath, and he workes repentance as well as gives remiſſiion of ſins, and I know I may look to the free grace of God in Chriſt, for grace as well as for glory, and alſo for all other things my ſoul ſtands in need of. Thus beloved a knowing ſoul will be able to reſt up on the free grace of God in Chriſt, although he ſee nothing at all but unworthineſs in himſelf. I do not ſay that every one that knows a little can do it, but he that knows what may be known with dilligent ſearch; and therefore when you ſee your ſouls in diſtreſs and anguiſh of ſpirit, and dare not beleeve, you may
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118935:6"/>ſafely conclude that although all that which they ſay againſt themſelves be never ſo true and much more; yet that is not the cauſe wherefore they do not beleeve, but their ignorance of God is the true cauſe thereof.</p>
               <p>Now beloved in the next place, I ſhall come to ſhew you how the knowledge of God, will keep men from preſumption alſo; and I pray you conſider it. Where the wiſdom and truth of God and his ſoveraignty is known, a perſon cannot go on in a courſe of diſobedience, for he very well knows, that God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not act below himſelfe, nor contrary to his Nature and Being, and that he cannot lie, nor alter the word that is gone forth of his mouth, but the deſtruction of him that goes on in his ſins wilfully, and preſumptuouſly, is as unalterable as God himſelf; for he cannot deny himſelf, but he and his Word and all his Decrees are one; there is no changing of God. Beloved we are apt to miſtake the Decrees of God, and to take them for ſome ſecret things which do not belong to us; indeed thoſe decrees that are ſecret they do not belong to us, and therefore let us not meddle with them by no means: but his decrees that concern the ſalvation and damnation of the ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> are revealed in the promiſes, and in the threatnings of the Scriptures, and are written for our warning and inſtruction; therefore let us look to it, for if we be found in thoſe obſtinate and rebellious courſes, that God hath threatened with deſtruct on, that decree, purpoſe and will of his, ſhall never be altered for the ſake of any man; no nor for the ſakes of all the men in the world: now he that knows this, dares not neglect his own ſalvation, nor put off repenting and turning to God, nor give up himſelf to work wickedneſs, for he knows the danger thereof. So that a knowing perſon you ſee is led to the obedience of faith as it were by a ſtraight line, that he cannot well go out of his way: it is with a man that knows God, my beloved, as it is with a man that is put in a way that he cannot well go out of; if you ſhould ſay to a man, friend keep you in this ſtraight path, go not out of it, there is an hedge on your right hand, all the way to the Town you are going, and a River on your left hand; now if the man ſhould miſs his way every one would wonder, becauſe his direction was ſo good. So great an advantage, an help hath a man to eternal life, that hath the knowledg of God, if he go out
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118935:6"/>of the way to it, it muſt be by an act of very great wilfulneſs. Thus I hope I have opened this point, plainly to all your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings; I ſhall now therefore come to the applycation of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. And in the firſt place, this Doctrin may ſerve to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn and reprove that greivous ſin of Ignorance, it is lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſee the greateſt part of men and women a mongſt us, ſo utterly void of the knowledg of God; O the graceleſneſs, and careleſneſs of men generally, how are they hardened againſt their own ſouls? I pray you conſider the greatneſs of the ſin, Beloved it muſt needs be a great ſin; firſt, becauſe the Lord hath very plainly manifeſted himſelf and his Son in his word; beloved, thoſe things that concern our ſalvation moſt immediately, are the moſt plainly revealed in the Word: there be ſome things hard it is true, but theſe things are not ſo hard that are ſpoken of God and of Chriſt; it is plain in the Scriptures that God is a God of Juſtice, Wiſdom, Power, Truth, Mercy, inviſible, eternal, unchangeable, one that knows the heart and the reines, and the like; and that Jeſus Chriſt hath died for ſinners, and that we are bound to live to him that died for us, and that he came to call ſinners to repentance, and that thoſe that beleeve and obey the Goſpel ſhall have eternal life: theſe truths are very plain; but although they be ſo, yet evident it is, that the greateſt number among us are ignorant of theſe things altogether. But further this adds to the ſin, that there is a great deal of means now more then hath been formerly, to bring men to knowledge, and it is altogether neglected, or elſe hearkened to ſo careleſly, that the Word is preached to the moſt of men altogether in vaine. I am perſwaded that if there were never a Word of God written at all, nor any other means to know the Lord by left us, but only the workes of creation and providence; if that theſe works of his were humbly and wiſely conſidered of, they would reveal more of the glory of God, then the moſt part among us do know, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt ſhining a mongſt us; O therefore conſider you that are ignorant of God, how inexcuſable and horrible your ſin is, what mean you to let the love of pleaſure, and profit, ſin and vanity, eat out the love of God, yea and of your own ſouls to? O how will you appear before the Lord one day, that have ſlighted the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118935:7"/>knowledg of him? well, let us pitty theſe men and mourn for them, if we cannot perſwade them to ſeek after God. I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid the ſaints do not with <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> weep in ſecret for theſe men; nor with <hi>David,</hi> guſh out rivers of tears for the ſin they live in, and the miſery that will come upon them: O let us pray for them, and be ſo much the more earneſt, by how much they are leſs ſenſible of there miſery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Secondly, If this be ſo that the knowledg of God hath ſo gracious a tendency to bring a perſon to Eternal life; then be ſure you make your Children, and thoſe that are under your charge know the Lord. Beloved, I ſpeak to thoſe that know him themſelves: I ſay to you, make him known to all you can, or to all you have an opportunity to ſpeak to, let your Children and Servants know what a God of mercy he is, yea of free grace, that looks to find no holineſs, nor repentance, no nor one good quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in thoſe he ſeeks to ſave. But he will work all theſe in the hearts of thoſe that come unto him; although they be never ſo bad, that will not hinder their acceptation with God, if ſo be they be but willing to be made good by him; nay though they ſhould not be freely willing to be made good, yet if they do but wait upon him in the uſe of the means he hath appointed, he will work their wills to be good; tell them Chriſt came for that end and purpoſe to work a cure upon the whole Man, even to take away all ſin, and alſo all the degreſs of it; yea he will take the ſtrongeſt enmity that is in the Souls of Men againſt himſelf and his wayes from them, and work the hearts of his worſt enemies to love him, and cauſe thoſe that love ſin beſt to hate it, if they do but wait at wiſdoms gate, and ſuffer the reproofs and inſtructions of Chriſt to enter into their Souls: and when you have preſſed their Souls with the knowledg of his goodneſs, and ſee them walk on ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly in the way of their own hearts: then ſay to them, O my Child, Servant, Neighbour, Friend, this path thou walkeſt in leadeth directly to Hell; it is impoſſible for thee in a courſe of wilful diſobedience to be ſaved: The <hi>Lord is Jehovah,</hi> and gives Being to his Word, he cannot lye nor repent; <hi>Heaven and earth ſhall paſs away, but his righteouſneſs and truth endures for ever;</hi> the word is gone forth of his mouth, and can never be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, he is the ſame forever, therefore hearken to his voice, or elſe thou muſt periſh for ever: and if you thus inſtruct your
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118935:7"/>Children and Servants in the knowledg of God, you ſhall by this means bring them to Eternal life: or if they miſs thereof, they ſhall be altogether left without excuſe; it is a moſt excellent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that you will do their poor Souls, to direct them thus in the ſtraight way to glory; for being thus inſtructed, they cannot well miſs of it; if they ſhould, it would be their grievous ſin. It is true they may make themſelves ten times more the children of Hell than they were before; but that is only their own fault, if after they have received the knowledg of the truth, they ſhall wilfully turn from it; this I confeſs is a ſin of a very dangerous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and will marvelouſly aggravate the ſin and condemnation of ſuch perſons; but let not that diſcourage you, Charity binds you to believe that you ſhall ſave their Souls: and if you do not do it, yet the means hath a proper tendency in it to bring about that end, and the fault will lye upon themſelves only; but you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered your own Souls, and this indeed is the caſe of all men where the light of the Goſpel comes, it will prove through their own default the great condemnation of thouſands; and yet for all that the Goſpel is a great mercy, and we have great cauſe to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for it, for it hath a bleſſed tendency to bring us to Salvation, if we through our own wickedneſs do not turn this grace into wantonneſs. I ſhall leave thus much with you at this time, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending what hath been ſaid to the bleſſing of the moſt High.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="exercise">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118935:8"/>
               <head>THE SECOND EXERCISE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 17.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>This is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THeſe words have been opened the laſt day, and one general concluſion drawn out of them, which was this; <hi>That the knowledge of God and of Chriſt, is the means of eternal life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This I hope was cleared to you the laſt time, and in part ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied; I ſhall make no repetition but begin where I left, and come to the uſes that remain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. And the next uſe that we are to make of it is this; if the knowledg of God be ſo advantagious toward the atainment of eternal life, then I beſeech you, let us take notice of it, and ſee the neceſſity of getting the knowledge thereof: I wil tell you what great need you have of it; <hi>Sollomon</hi> tels us, we cannot be good without it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.2. and it is evident that you can have no ſtrength againſt your corruptions without it; it is a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent means to help a man againſt ſin; yea againſt thoſe ſins he may be moſt naturally inclined to, ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.8. to the 17. <hi>He keepeth the paths of judgement, and preſerveth the way of his ſaints; then ſhall thou underſtand righteouſneſſe, and judgement, and equity; yea every good path,</hi> ſaith <hi>Sollomon.</hi> Yea but when ſhal a man have this glorious aſſiſtance to walk thus evenly, and to know every good path, and to be preſerved and kept in ſo even a way; it is a bleſſed condition indeed, if a man knew how to attain it; why that you ſhall ſee in the two next verſes; <hi>When wiſdom entereth into thine heart; and knowledge is pleaſant unto thy ſoul; deſcretion ſhall preſerve thee, underſtanding ſhall keep thee.</hi> Take notice I pray you, it is knowledge you ſee that muſt be the means to keep a man from all thoſe evils, froward, dark, and crooked wayes, ſpoken of in the 12, 13, 14, 15, verſes.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118935:8"/>
               <p> But it may be you will ſay, I do not find it ſo hard a thing to fight againſt all thoſe ſins; I am not inclined to brawling, and bitterneſs, it is a luſt of another nature that I am troubled with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, wantonneſs is my ſin, that I am moſt apt to fall into? eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcially when I meet with fit companions; if I fall into an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots company, then am I preſently ſnared.</p>
               <p>Now read the 16 verſe, and you ſhall ſee what a bulwork the knowledge of God is againſt the danger of ſuch a ſinfull temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; mark it I pray you, <hi>to deliver thee,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>from the ſtrange woman, even from the ſtranger, which flattereth with her words.</hi> You ſee Beloved how ſtrongly a man is fortified againſt the ſtrongeſt temptation, that is furniſhed with this precious grace; Harlots have tricks to ſpeak with their eyes, and this is temptation enough to a man inclined to that ſin; but when ſhe ſhall be ſo impudent as to ſpeak plain engliſh, and fall to flatter a man with words, now the temptation is much ſtronger but yet you ſee this means will keep a man in ſuch a time, and this is the reaſon of it, the knowledg of God works that faith in a man, and that fear of God, and brings the ſoul into acquaintance and ſweet communion together with him; ſo that a man will not grieve the ſpirit of Chriſt, nor break company with him for all the pleaſures in the world; and look how it is in this, ſo it will be in any other caſe whatſoever, if there be any corruption that a man finds harder to be mortified then ordinary, it will help him againſt it, and without this you muſt not look to get victory over ſin, ſpecially thoſe ſins, or that ſame one curruption, that is more then ordinarily ſtrong; for you moſt know that the Divell can tie a man faſt enough with one cord, and keep him as faſt in priſon when there is one door locked upon him, as if there were twenty: now you cannot expect help out of his paw, without the knowledge of God, for if you would have grace, and ſtrength, to mortifie ſin, you muſt go to Chriſt for it; and if you go to him, it muſt be by faith; and if that be gotten, it muſt be by the knowledg of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly you will never get ſuch a faith as will ſtand you in any ſtead, or do you any good in the day of temptation without it, for it muſt be the knowledge of the nature of God, that is a God of love, and of Free-grace, and one that can abound in pardoning, and that he ſent Jeſus Chriſt to ſave ſinners: till a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118935:9"/>man knows that Chriſt is a Saviour, that he layes both the firſt and the laſt ſtone thereof, and that a man cannot be one hairs breadth better then he is by nature, till the Spirit of Chriſt hath mended him, and that the firſt work that a man can do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably, is to come to Chriſt for a cure both for his heart and life. I ſay, till a man knows this, he can never be eſtabliſhed in beleeving, you ſhall ſee the reaſon of it preſently; a man that wants this knowledge he gathers ſuch grounds to build his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence upon, that are ſwept away in the day of temptation; it is with his faith, juſt as it is with a houſe that is built upon the ſands, where the tide comes, when the wind and the tide comes ſtrong, away goes the ground, and the houſe together; even ſo is it with an ignorant mans faith, for this is one of his beſt incourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to beleeve, when he conſiders that his former ſinfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane life, is the road way to hell; then he endeavours to leave thoſe courſes, and falls to prayer, and to reading, and hearing, and this he takes to be ſuch a change, that now he thinks he is a child of God, and that all the promſes belong unto him: but then when his old luſts, appear again and take hold on him, then he falls to utter diſpair, and concludes that he was but an hypocrite at the beſt, and that there is no hope for him; and one day he thinks it is a duty to beleeve, and another day he thinks there is no ground for him ſo to do; and thus the poot ſoul is unſtable and toſſed like a ſhip in a tempeſt, one while mounted up to heaven, and another while thrown down into the deep, and melted a way with trouble. But now the ſoul that knows God, and did ſee in him a ground to beleeve at the firſt, without any works of righteouſneſs done before-hand, and that knew Jeſus Chriſt came to ſave from ſin, and to give repentance, as well as eternall life, and did at the firſt caſt himſelf upon him, not as a ſaint, but as a ſinner: this man if he ſhould fall as low as he was before, yet he will ſee at leaſt the ſame ground to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve us he did ſee at the firſt. I ſpeak not this to incourage any any to renew there ſins, I hope you wil not make ſo bad a uſe of it; but if any ſhould, yet is the doctrin of grace a truth, that muſt be preached, though ſome ſhould wreſt it to their own deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the knowledge of God will carry a man through the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118935:9"/>worſt of troubles; if he ſhould come into <hi>Jobs</hi> caſe, that his wife ſhould be ſtrange, and his children and eſtate ſwept away, and his godly friends turned his enemies; yet would he be able to ſay with him, <hi>though he kill me, yet I will, and I can truſt in him, for I know my Redeemer liveth.</hi> Thus when a man can ſay with <hi>Paul, I know whom I have beleeved,</hi> by being able to ſee the power, wiſdom, truth, and goodneſs of God; it will be ſuch a rock for him to ſet his feet upon, that will keep him from ſinking in the worſt of times.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, a man that knows God, will ſerve him with that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light that another man cannot do; an ignorant man may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that it is a duty to hear and to pray, and the like; but he hath no comfort in theſe ordinances, but yet he uſes them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he dares do no otherwiſe; but a man that knows God, ſees ſuch a beauty in God, that he goes to ſeek him with much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, he knows they be means appointed of God, to bring him into neerer communion with him, and to give him a more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſight of God; and therefore it is a work well peaſing to him, and he goes about it with as much content as men uſe to go to their recreations; but the other goes to the ſame work, as one goes to a trade, that he is ſet to againſt his will, he does it unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and unwillingly, and will get from it if he can; and ſo wil the man from duties that knows not God, if he can but find a way to eſcape the rebukes of his own conſcience. Now therefore I pray you make it your firſt &amp; greateſt work to get the knowledg of God: with all diligence ſeek for it, for the priſe thereof is greater then ſilver, choice gold, or rubies; therefore ſearch for it more then for hidden treaſures.</p>
               <p>There is two means that I will direct you to make uſe of for the getting of this knowledge.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, the conſideration of the works of God; if a man do but humbly and wiſely obſerve his great works, they will ſhew forth much of his glory; if you look to the heavens, and conſider what a great diſtance they are ſpread above the earth, and compaſſing it round about, and ſee thoſe glorious creatures the Sun, Moon and Stars, roul about, to ſerve poor worms, and lumps of clay; how plainly will they teach you that the creator of them is a God of infinite goodneſs: for before ever he did create either them, or the men for whoſe ſakes they were created,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118935:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118935:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118935:11"/>the Lord did perfectly underſtand all the wickedneſs that would in time be commited by every one of them; and yet it did not hinder him in this great worke, but he hath done it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues to uphold it, notwithſtanding all that unworthineſs that is found among the children of men: and if you look to the Earth, and the Seas, and ſee them hang in a round lump, in the midſt of the heavens, cleaving together, and the waters not over-flowing the earth; this great work will tell you that the Creator thereof is infinite in power, wiſdom, and goodneſs: and if you conſider how the Earth and the Seas are ſtored with variety of Creatures, with ſeverall hoſts of creatures, and yet not a man nor a beaſt, nor a fiſh, nor a fowl, no worm, nor any creature, more nor leſs; but God takes care every day how they ſhall be fed: the wild beaſts of the wilderneſs that no man takes care of have there meat and there drink every day from the hand of God; Oh, how do theſe gracious acts of his every day preach the glory of his great name to all conſidering men, that will but ſet themſelves to mind the great wiſdom, patience, power, truth, and mercy of God, that ſhines forth in the works of God. Add to this the conſideration of the great provocations, wherewith he is provoked every day, by them he hath done all theſe great things for; how many oaths, lies unclean, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, cruel, and abominable evils, of all kindes, are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted every day by them; and yet the Lord is patient and kind for all that: Oh be perſwaded to mind his dayly compaſſions, that are ſo clearly manifeſted, that you may learn to love and truſt in him, and that you may be drawn to repentance; remember that the long ſuffering, bounty, and goodneſs of God, is extended for that very end, therefore abuſe it not.</p>
               <p>Again, if you would caſt your eyes abroad, and take notice of the works of God, that he is doing dayly, it would much help you in the underſtanding of his juſtice, wiſdom, mercy, &amp; al ſeeing eye, over the world: Beloved, there be evident demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Lords warchfull eye and care over the ſaints, when they have been under oppreſſion and have cried to God, he hath ſeen their affliction and heard their cry, and hath marvellouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered them, and hath brought down their oppreſſors when they have been too mighty for men to deal withal, and hath given
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118935:11"/>them ſuch a reward of their tyranny ſometimes, that whoſoever did but obſerve the judgement, might wel know from whence the ſtroke came, and for what cauſe; it is not for want of the Lords manifeſting of himſelf that he is no more known in the world, but it is our want of taking notice of his works, that makes us igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of him.</p>
               <p>Next I pray you conſider his word, for there he hath more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly revealed himſelf, make therefore the Scriptures your conſtant ſtudy, you have there very many deſcriptions and characters of God, and of the Lord Jeſus; I pray you labour to underſtand them; you have a very notable diſcription of God in <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.15. there he cals himſelf <hi>the God of Abraham, the God of Iſaac, and the God of Jacob;</hi> and tels us that this is his <hi>name and his memorial unto all generations;</hi> note it I pray you well, that you may know him by it.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay it may be, what is it to us that he is the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob?</hi> how ſhall we know him ever the better for this name?</p>
               <p>Yes Beloved, you may know the Lord much the better for this name if you conſider this, that <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> were true Beleevers; it is as much as if he ſhould tell you, that he will be the God of all thoſe that walk in the ſteps of theſe men: ſo that whoſoever beleeves and comes to God, with uprightneſs of heart, depending upon him for ſtrength to walk in the ſteps of <hi>Abraham</hi> he will be the God of ſuch a one; and what is it to have God to be our God? that you ſhall fee is a great bleſſing; it is as much as if he ſhould tell us, that all the ſufficiency that is in himſelf, his power, wiſdom, mercy, truth and all his goodneſs, it ſhall be exerciſed and put forth for our good.</p>
               <p>Another Name that God aſcribes to himſelf, who beſt knows his own Name, we find in <hi>Exod.</hi> 63. there the Lord tels <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that although, their fathers knew him not by his Name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> yet they ſhould know him by this Name: that is as much as to ſay, I am he, that have my Being of my ſelf, and I give Being to all things elſe, and I give a Being to my Word, and that you ſhall ſee, for I will make my promiſes good unto you, you ſhall ſee the ſulfilling of them. Oh if this Name of God were known and beleeved in, how would it advance godlineſs in the hearts and lives of men? if men did beleeve that he would give a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118935:12"/>Being to his promiſſes, how would they truſt in him; and likewiſe if they did beleeve that he would give Being to his threatenings, they would learn to fear him, and to give up themſelves to holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe I pray you labour to know Chriſt, and to mind the ends of his coming, he hath the name of a Saviour, labour to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the meaning thereof, whether he came to Save men from Hell only, or to ſave them from ſin likewiſe; or whether he came to take away ſome ſin, or all ſins, and to bring every thought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the obedience of his will; and whether he is not a Prince as well as a Saviour, and wil reign in the conſciences, and rule and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the converſation of thoſe that he will ſave. I am not now ſo much a teaching you the knowledg of God, as a endeavouring to perſwade you to ſtudy the word of God, and to make it your buſineſs to get the knowledge of God, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt. I have laid before your eyes in ſome meaſure the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of this jewel; I pray you labour to get it, <hi>with all your gettings, get knowledge,</hi> and increaſe in it dayly, for it is a pearl of great worth.</p>
               <p>But it may be that ſome of you may ſay, that if knowledg were ſo excellent a thing as I would make it, wherefore then doth <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> that had ſo much of it and knew it ſo well, ſpeak of it as he doth <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.18. <hi>For in much wiſdom, is much grief, and he that increaſeth knowledg, increaſeth ſorrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The anſwering of this would take up too much time; I ſhall therefore leave it to the after-noon. Let us commend what hath been ſaid, to the bleſſing of the Almighty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="exercise">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118935:12"/>
               <head>THE THIRD EXERCISE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 17.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And this is life eternal, that they might know thee, the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THeſe words have been opened already, and in part ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled; I will not ſtand to repeate, but begin where I left.</p>
               <p>You know I was come to anſwer an Objection that might ſeem to be grounded on the words of the Preacher. Now I ſhall ſhew you how this Doctrine and that text are fairly reconciled together; a man that knows God may eaſily procure to himſelf ſorrow, by his knowledg; and yet knowledg is not a tittle the leſſe worth for all that: A perſon that knows God and walks up to his knowledg, wiſely and holily, ſhall never want enemies, that either with open force, or by ſecret practiſes will work him ſorrow enough, as you may ſee in the caſe of <hi>David,</hi> in the 1 of <hi>Samuel</hi> 18.14, 15. <hi>And David behaved himſelf wiſely in all his wayes; and the Lord was with him.</hi> And what does this procure to <hi>David?</hi> will not <hi>Saul</hi> love him and honour him now? no, ſaith the text <hi>When Saul ſaw that he behaved himſelf very wiſely, he was afraid of him:</hi> and what then? why then, he muſt have <hi>Sauls</hi> elder daughter to ingage him to ſuch a ſervice as might cauſe him to fall by the hand of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and then he muſt have at laſt his younger daughter, that ſhe might be a ſnare unto him; and when al this would not do, then <hi>Saul</hi> becomes his open enemy, and purſues him for his life with open violence: and this muſt other men expect as well as <hi>David</hi> if they be men of knowledg, and walk wiſely, and be like to be of uſe either in Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth thoſe that are not ſound at the core, will indeavour to work them ſorrow; if this man ſay they know the peoples right ſo well, and the Magiſtrates duty ſo well, and begin to talk
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118935:13"/>thus, he will ſoon get the power out of our hands, down with him; and ſo likewiſe if a man be able to ſpeak of God, or the things of God, to the comfort and edification of others, a bad Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry will ſoon be deviſing ſomething to work this man grief; Oh ſay they, if this man get into credit with the people, we ſhall ſoon grow into contempt, therefore let us remove him further if it be poſſible; and yet although this and much more then this be true, knowledg though it be attended with the croſſe, yet is it a jewel worth getting, with labour and travel, which although it may coſt a man dear, yet it will bear its own charges when it is gotten.</p>
               <p>Another Objection may ariſe in the hearts of ſome, from the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Knowledg puffeth up, but charity edifieth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This may ſeem to caſt ſome contempt upon knowledg, therefore I muſt take a little time to open this text unto you. I therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to look into the beginning of the 7 chapter, and there you ſhall find, that the <hi>Corinths</hi> wrote an epiſtle or letter to <hi>Paul,</hi> for ſatisfaction in ſome caſes of conſcience; among others this is one, that ſome of the members of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> went to the Idols temple, &amp; together with the Idolaters did eat of the the meat ſacrificed to Idols, to the offence of ſome, and ſeandal of the Goſpel; now as it ſeems to me the Apoſtle in that 8 chapter layes down their arguments, which they made uſe of for the defence of this practiſe, and there in that place he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers them; firſt upon their own ground, that if it ſhould be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, that indeed they did proceed upon grounds of knowledg, as it was ſuppoſed by them they did, to eat of that meat, yet there practiſe muſt needs be evil; the unbeleeving <hi>Corinths</hi> ſtill being hardened by this means in their old ſinfull way of eating it, to the defiling of their conſciences, and the weak brethren like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, would be drawn upon doubtfull grounds to do it, to the wounding of their conſciences; and this <hi>Paul</hi> tels them could not ſtand with charity, and gives them to underſtand, that a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg ſeparated from charity, or that acted in oppoſition to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, would prove of no better uſe, but to puff up the heart of him in whom it was; for when men will imply their parts to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wit the weak, and bring crafty arguments to defend ſinful acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; it is no wonder that ſuch a knowledg as this tends to, ſwell and puffe up the heart of him, that thus abuſeth his wits: now
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118935:13"/>although the <hi>Corinths</hi> did plead grounds of knowledg for their practiſes, and the Apoſtle there gives it the ſame name, yet you may ſee by what follows in the 9. &amp; 10 Chapters, that he did not account their practiſe, their light, and their knowledg, but their ſin and their errour; for ſaith he in the 10 chap. <hi>Flee from Idolatry;</hi> and if it were Idolatry it could not be knowledg; and there the Apoſtle brings clear inſtances to prove it ſo; one from the Lords Supper, there he tels them that they, <hi>that eat and drink that to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether are one communion, one bread;</hi> and that, <hi>whoſoever eat of Iſraels ſacrifices were partakers of their Altar,</hi> and tels them, <hi>it was the table of Divels, that they eat of, and that they could not eat of it, and of the Lords table both; bidding them not to provoke the Lord.</hi> asking them if they <hi>were ſtronger than he,</hi> ſo that whoſoever minds theſe arguments, and conſiders wherefore they are brought, will ſee that here is nothing againſt knowledge, but againſt a proud conceit of it; for indeed the more any man knows of God, the humbler he will be and when you ſee any man proud, and puffed up with his knowledg, you may be ſure he is no more indeed &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, but a conceited fool; therefore I pray you take heed to uſe all the means the Scriptures do preſcribe for the getting of knowledg; hear, pray, read, and make the word your dayly medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. <hi>David</hi> had <hi>more underſtanding then his teachers,</hi> by this means; therefore uſe it, and whatſoever you can find in the word of truth, to be a means preſcribed for the getting and increaſing of it; I beſeech you uſe with all faithfulneſs, diligence, and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and he that thus ſeeketh it ſhall find it, and he that findeth it, findeth the ready way to eternal life; and ſo much for this Uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. I ſhal now come to the next uſe, and that muſt be a word of exhortation, to all thoſe that know God, or profeſs to know him; Beloved, there are many duties lying upon you wherein you are eminently concerned; I ſhall lay ſome few of them before you at this time.</p>
               <p>The firſt is this, if you know much or any thing at all, take heed of abuſing your knowledg to the ſervice of any ſin; there be ſeveral wayes by which this may be done. Firſt, beware you do not uſe your knowledg to defend ſin, or to make fair pretences for it when men pervert there knowledg for ſo baſe an end as that is, and indeavour to turn the ſimple-bearted out of the way, by making excuſes either for bad principles, or for evil practiſes,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118935:14"/>it is a very dangerous ſin, when a man uſeth knowledg to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt himſelf, or others, and by that very means that tends to lead him to eternal life, he poſteth the faſter toward hell: how ſinfull and provoking muſt this needs be to the Lord? the more precious any thing is, the more abominable it is to abuſe it.</p>
               <p>Next take heed you make not knowledg a ſtalking horſe for pride or covetouſneſs, or any other curſed luſt; if a man ſhould preach Chriſts Goſpel never ſo painfully, and yet his ſecret end be the advanemcent of his own honor; this man ſerves pride and vain glory in what he doth, and not the Lord Jeſus: and ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if a man preach the truth never ſo diligently, all his dayes, but doth it for a livings ſake, and not for the works ſake, he will be found in what he hath done, a ſervant of covetouſneſs, and not of Chriſt: and when men can go from place to place, for tenor twenty pound a year more wages, it is in my judgment ſuch a ſad ſelling of the gifts of God for money, if gifted they be, that it would make a man tremble to think of it: I do not ſpeak as if wages were altogether unlawful, if it be Chriſts wages, a reward freely contributed by ſuch as are won thereunto for the love they bear to the Goſpel, then I know it is not unlawful, ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward may be received; neither do I ſpeak as if there were no lawfulneſs in any remove; I know it is lawful when a mans work and not his wages is the cauſe thereof.</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſay no more to this, becauſe I am not ſpeaking to an Auditory of Preachers; but I intreat you al to look to your hearts, that you uſe your knowledg, not for the advancing of your ſelves in the world, but for the glory of God, the good of your own ſouls, and the good of the ſouls of others; learn by it more to fear and to truſt in the Lord dayly, learn to delight in him by it, and let it be a means of bringing you into a neerer communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him every day, and forget not to communicate your knowledge to others but be diſtilling of it dayly into their ſouls; it is true ignorant ones ſhould be asking their fathers, and their elders, and ſuch as can teach them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.7. but ſeeing they are commonly backward to their duty, therefore every knowing perſon ſhould be wiſely, and humbly forward to draw them to the knowledg of him.</p>
               <p>Another duty you muſt be intreated to take ſpecial notice of, is this; if you profeſſe to know God, remember to live holily,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118935:14"/>you are ingaged to it eminently, therefore I yray you above all things <hi>let your converſation be as it becometh the Goſpel, and let every one of you that nameth the name of Chriſt, depart from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> 2 Tim 2.19. The Apoſtle <hi>Titus</hi> 1.16. ſpeaks of a ſort of men that <hi>profeſſe to know God, but in works they deny him,</hi> being <hi>abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> (ſaith he) and well may he ſay ſo, for it is abominable indeed, to know God and to carry ones ſelf as if they had never heard, or known that there is a God. I beſeech you take heed, that none of you be found among that abominable nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber; but let your works manifeſt that you are ſuch as doe indeed know the Lord, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns every one of you to <hi>ſhine as lights in this preſent evil world,</hi> you have no other way to <hi>put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men,</hi> at leſt no way without this; although you ſpeak never ſo know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and holily, that will not ſerve the turn, actions ſpeak lowder then words; therefore I pray you let us ſtudy holineſs, without it we cannot ſee the Lord hereafter, nor pleaſe him here; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it we ſhall do no good in the world, nor draw any ignorant ones to the knowledg of God, or love of his truth, but contrarily you will be a means to drive men from Chriſt, and to cauſe them to abhor his truth; without holineſs you neither will nor can be of any better uſe in the world, then to be ſtumbling blocks for blind men to tumble over into hell; therefore let us caſt away <hi>every work of darkneſs; and put on the whole armor of light,</hi> ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be holy in all manner of converſation, and bring forth thoſe fruits of humility, patience, juſtice, mercifulneſs, love, ſelf-denial, and the reſt of the fruits of the ſpirit; that the world may ſee that God is in you of a truth, and that they may be able to ſay theſe men do indeed direct us into the path that leads to eternal life; but if you walk contrary to holineſs, you will do no good but hurt with all your knowledg; the better you talk the more miſchief you will do, the world will be apt to think there is no beleeving you whatever you ſay, but the better you ſpeak of God, the more they will queſtion whether there be a God or no, for ſay they, if theſe men did beleeve as they ſpeak, would they live as they do? therefore if you would not be inſtruments to bring the world into ſtark Atheiſme live holily; &amp; if this follow not, namely, there turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Atheiſts, yet that wil follow which is bad enough, the world wil certainly conclude, that you are hypocrites and that you have your bad ends in all your good words, and ſo they will be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118935:15"/>brought to have an evil opinion of all your undertakings, and ſo you will be in no capacity to do them any good; therefore I pray you conſider and beware of all thoſe ſins that will procure ſo much miſchief, eſpecially beware of thoſe ſins the World is ſo apt to charge upon you; it is a charge the World hath had againſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors this thirty years and more in my knowledg, that they are a proud people, and none ſo covetous as they, and that they be uncharitable, and do no good in the World. Now I pray you Brethren, conſider whether this be true or no, if this be a ſlander, then you may bear it the better, but if your proud carriage, covetous words or actions, cloſe-fiſtedneſs, and the like, have procured this report, then I beſeech you repent, and let your attire be below your Rank, rather than above it; let your words and actions be free from Covetouſneſs, give not the World oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion any more to ſpeak or to think ſo hardly of you, abound more in doing good, according unto your ability, and let no more ſuch complaints be heard by your means; it were better a great deal that you were out of the World, than that you ſhould live in it to bring forth ſuch fruit as will cauſe the Goſpel to have an evill ſavour in the World.</p>
               <p>There is one duty more that I would intreat you to mind; if the knowledg of God and of Chriſt be of ſo great uſe, then let us not forget to be thankful, that he is pleaſed to afford us ſuch a gracious means of knowledg as the Word of Truth is; Oh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of the greatneſs of his Mercy, that the Lord ſhould be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to write ſo many plain and gracious characters of his great and glorious Name, and ſend it to us, and that we ſhould at leaſt ſee ſo much of his back parts, as may incourage and inable us to beleeve, and that he ſhould ſo preſerve the Scriptures as he hath done, although they have gone through ſo many foul hands, and he hath very plainly manifeſted the ends of our Lord Jeſus Chriſts coming into the World, and thereby opened a door of Salvation unto us poor unworthy ſinners; this ſhould cauſe us to exalt his Name, and tell forth his praiſes and wonderful works with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, that we may affect the hearts of others, and cauſe them to love the Lord, and to truſt in him for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 5. I have but one Uſe more to make of this Point, and that is a word to Men that know not God, I muſt let you know that it is your duty to be thankful alſo, and although you do not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118935:15"/>know the Father, nor the Son, yet that you might have known them, and may yet poſſibly come to know them, it is a great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and although you care not to know him, yet it is his mercy nevertheleſs, in affording you ſo gracious a means of knowledg. I ſay although you neither do, nor will know him, yet is he merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for all that: but that is not all I have to ſay to you, take one word more, and ſet it upon your hearts; if you do not come to know him, it will be more tolerable for <hi>Sodom,</hi> for <hi>Turks,</hi> for <hi>Indians,</hi> and for the brutiſheſt of Men, than for you, they that do not know him and glorifie him, according to the means affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them, ſhall not be excuſed. But Oh how inexcuſeable ſhall you be that live in <hi>England,</hi> nay in thoſe places where you have had the Goſpel plainly and plentifully Preached unto you; temem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that when you come before the Judgement ſeat of Chriſt, it will not be poſſible for you to find an excuſe for your ignorance; which of you have humbly and conſcionably ſought for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and have not found it; have you uſed that direction <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> gives you, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4. how often have you read the Scriptures over, and pondered them in your hearts, it may be not twice in all your lives; I pray you tell me, when Chriſt ſhall come to ask you at the day of Account, whether you had not a word called a Bible that did teſtifie of him, and of his Father, and that gave you direction how you might attain Eternal Life, what will you then ſay to him? if you ſhould ſay, that although you had the Scriptures, yet you underſtood them not; if you will but give him leave to ask you whoſe fault that was; whether this did not come to paſs through your own neglect of his word, and mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things of leſs moment; I marvel whether you will not then be ſpeechleſs yea or no. Again if he ſhall ask you whether you nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knew nor heard of any man living in the Age with you, that was able to direct you in the way to Eternal life; will not theſe queſtions ſtop your mouths, and let you ſee that your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation is juſt upon you? Conſider this, and let it prevail with you to cauſe you to ſeek after the Knowledg of God in time: but if you will ſtill mind preſent vanities more than Eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, you cannot ſay but you had a fair warning, and that your Blood is upon your own heads; and ſo much for this time, and for this Point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="exercise">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118935:16"/>
               <head>THE FOURTH EXERCISE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 17.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true God, and Jeſus Christ whom thou haſt ſent.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>I Shall now come to this ſecond Head of Doctrine in this Text, namely, <hi>The Lords being called the only true God.</hi> Now the word <hi>Only</hi> ſignifieth one, and no more but one; but if you fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ask what the word <hi>True</hi> meaneth; the anſwer muſt be this, the Lord by this Word oppoſeth himſelf to, or differenceth himſelf from all others, that are no Gods by Nature, and ſo no Gods in truth.</p>
               <p>For the right underſtanding of this one only true God, I muſt ſhew you that there are two ſorts of Gods, beſides this one only True God: I ſhall ſhew you who theſe be, wherefore they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gods.</p>
               <p>For the firſt ſort of them you muſt know, that there are Gods by Office; and that you ſhall ſee in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 82. there you ſhall ſee a ſort of Men called Gods, not for their goodneſs ſake, but for their Office ſake: and therefore hath the Lord put this Title upon Magiſtrates and Rulers, that we might learn to obey them in the Lord.</p>
               <p>A ſecond ſort of Gods you may find noted in <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.17. there they are called by the name of New Gods; and in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 81.9. they are call'd by the Name of ſtrange Gods; theſe are Idols, the work of mens hands, which they make to Worſhip, or at leaſt they make them to Worſhip God by them; theſe are falſe Gods, even the Work of Error, and the fruit of mens folly, no way deſerving the name of Gods, but only to rebuke the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs of men, for adoring the devices of their own hearts, and eſteeming ſo highly the work of their own fingers. But now the only true God is he that made Heaven and Earth, unto whom the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118935:16"/>name of God in a proper ſence is only due; and that is the Point I would have you note;</p>
               <p>Doct. 2. <hi>That there is one only true God, and there is no other Gods but he.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall intreat you to note how plentiful and plainly this is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Scriptures, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.35, 39. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee it was ſhewed that thou mighteſt know that the Lord he is God, there is none elſe beſide him.</hi> The words are very plain, this is that truth that God would have <hi>Iſrael</hi> know, and therefore he ſhewed it to them, that there was one God, and there was none elſe beſide him; and therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> preſſeth it again in <hi>Verſe</hi> 39. that <hi>Iſrael ſhould know it and conſider it;</hi> that the Lord which had made them hear his voice from Heaven, and ſhewed them his great fire on Earth, <hi>verſe</hi> 36. and that had loved their Fathers, and choſen their Seed, and brought them out of <hi>Egypt, verſe</hi> 37. and that had driven out thoſe mighty Nations, and given their Land to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> that this God is God both in Heaven and in Earth, and that there is no other God beſide him. And in the ſixth Chapter, and fourth Verſe, <hi>Hear O Iſrael, the Lord our God is one Lord,</hi> and in the 10.17. he is called the <hi>God of Gods, and Lord of Lords.</hi> And ſo it is ſaid alſo in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4. that <hi>there is no other Gods but one;</hi> and in the ſixth verſe it is ſaid, that <hi>to us there is but one God;</hi> and in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. he is there noted by ſuch deſcriptions as do abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly clear the truth of this.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he is therefore called the <hi>King Eternal, Immortal, Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</hi> Now this Word, the King, ſhews plainly, that he that is the ſupream Being is but One, and that this one Being is from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and continues to Eternity, and is one inviſible Spirit, more excellent and glorious than can be beheld with the Eye of fleſh.</p>
               <p>Again, he is there called the <hi>only wiſe God;</hi> which is as much as to ſay, it implies ſo much, that he and he alone is that one Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſimple Being, who <hi>is the well-ſpring and fountain of all wiſdom;</hi> look alſo <hi>Pſal,</hi> 86.8, 10. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 37.16. and 44.24. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.10, 11, 12. I might alledg a multitude of places more for the proof of this if need were, but theſe may ſuffice to evidence it to us that there <hi>is one, and but one Eternal God,</hi> that is the only fountain &amp; perfect on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118935:17"/>of all <hi>Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs;</hi> yea the cauſe of all other Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings whatſoever, and he from whom all Creatures more and leſs have their Being, and are preſerved; yea, from this Infinite Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>that fils Heaven and Earth with his glory, Jer.</hi> 23.24. but is not contained in them, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.27. but contains the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures within himſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. I ſay from him all Grace and comfort whatſover deſerveth the Name of good is extended and given of free and meer Grace to the whole Creation; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this I beſeech you hold faſt, that there is one, and but one Eternal, Infinite, Unchangeable, and Inviſible God, from whom all things were &amp; are for evermore, who is alone to be feared and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, and to be worſhipped in ſpirit and in truth, and to be had in eſpecial reverence of all that come about him. But I ſhall ſay no more to this, truſting none of you will deny it, but ſhall come in the next place to ſhew you that what is Attributed unto the true God, and that which in a proper ſence is only meet to be aſcribed unto him, is alſo aſcribed both unto the Lord Jeſus, and alſo to the Holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>Now therefore for the firſt of theſe: you ſhall ſee how preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and plainly the Scriptures do acknowledg the Lord Jeſus to be God, and do give as much honour unto him as is, or as can be given to the Father, look <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.9. the words are theſe: <hi>For unto us a Child is born, unto us a Son is given, and the Government ſhall be upon his ſhoulders.</hi> Here you ſee plainly that this is ſpoken of the Lord Jeſus, and can be applyed to no other. Now you ſhall ſee what is there further ſaid of him, and what Names and Titles are Attributed to him in the following words, <hi>and his Name ſhall be called wonderful Counſellor, the mighty God, the everlaſting Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Prince of Peace;</hi> now tell me I pray you what ever was, or can be aſcribed to the Father more than this, to call him <hi>The mighty God,</hi> what can be in that word leſs than this, the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of him to be the Author and Fountain of might and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: likewiſe to call him <hi>The everlaſting Father;</hi> what can it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie leſs than his being the firſt cauſe of all things, and he that by himſelf alone, and his own might and power hath produced them, and brought them forth. Again, look <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8. <hi>I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the ending, ſaith the Lord, which is, and which was, and which is to come; the Almighty.</hi> I pray you think of it, for my part I cannot ſee that in theſe termes, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118935:17"/>and ending, firſt and laſt, as it follows in <hi>verſe</hi> 11. there can be leſs than the magnifying of himſelf to be the firſt cauſe of all things, and the upholder of them to all Eternity, and the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of himſelf in them to be even from eternity the only true God; for if there had been any other either before him, or together with him from Eternity, then could he not be called the firſt; and for this word, <hi>the Almighty,</hi> it is ſo full a word to expreſs the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head by, that I cannot tell where you can find a fuller, for if in him be all might, then no part of this Almightineſs can be found in any other, and ſo much this word, <hi>the Almighty,</hi> muſt needs ſignifie; now if you compare this with <hi>verſ.</hi> 17, 18. you will clearly ſee that all this the Lord Jeſus ſpeaks of himſelf, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cannot be leſs than God. Again, if you pleaſe to look <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. there you will find the Apoſtle ſaying, <hi>that he thought it not robbery to be equal with God;</hi> but if he had not been truly God indeed, it could not have been leſs than robbery, either ſo to ſpeak, or ſo to think, for it is impoſſible for any created Being that is the Off-ſpring of God, to reckon it ſelf equal with God, without committing thoſe moſt horrible great ſins of Pride and Blaſphemy, and therefore it is moſt evident that he that thinks it no Robbery to be equal with <hi>God,</hi> cannot be leſs than <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and if you pleaſe to look in the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>John,</hi> chap. 5. Verſe 20. there you ſhall find the name of the True <hi>God</hi> aſcribed to <hi>Jefus Chriſt;</hi> but no where in all the Scriptures ſhall you find that the name of the <hi>true God</hi> is uſed in a figurative ſence; but he to whom this honour is given, muſt needs be the moſt high <hi>God.</hi> Further, in <hi>John</hi> 20.28. there you ſhall find <hi>Thomas</hi> acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him to be both his <hi>Lord, and his God;</hi> but if it had not been a Title fully due unto the Lord Jeſus, both he and <hi>Thomas</hi> had greatly failed, the one in giving, and the other in taking this great glory to himſelf.</p>
               <p>Now I ſhall come in the next place to ſhew you that the Holy Spirit alſo is <hi>God,</hi> and that that which is aſcribed unto him in the Scriptures, could not be aſcribed to him if he were not <hi>God.</hi> Firſt conſider what Names and Titles the Holy Spirit taketh unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 57.15. <hi>Thus ſaith the high and lofty one that inhabiteth eternity, whoſe Name is holy.</hi> Mark it ſpray you, for any Man to call himſelf by the Name of the moſt High and lofty One, that is inferior to the <hi>moſt High,</hi> it is impoſſible; or to aſcribe to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118935:18"/>
                  <hi>Eternity,</hi> or the Name of the <hi>Holy One,</hi> that is not the moſt High and Eternal God, it cannot be; but this is ſpoken by the Spirit, and that of himſelf, as you may ſee by that which follows in the next words, <hi>I dwell in the high and holy place: with him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones.</hi> Here you ſee by the gracious work and Office here undertaken, who it is that ſpeaks, for it is granted of all men that it is the proper work and office of the Spirit to be the Sanctifier, and comforter of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God: and that it is he which doth refreſh and revive, and comfort the hearts of poor, humble, contrite ſinners; but if men ſhould deny it, yet the Scriptures do clearly witneſs it; I will name you but one Text for this, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.16, 17, 18. there Chriſt tells his Diſciples, <hi>That he will pray the Father to ſend them this Comforter, this holy Spirit,</hi> that ſhould abide with them for ever, and dwell both in them and with them, and they ſhould not be left comfortleſs; whence you ſee plainly that the in-dwelling preſence of the Holy Spirit in the heart, is that which doth ſupport and comfort, and revive it; and he that doth this gracious work for and in the ſouls of Gods poor people, is that high and lofty one that inhabiteth Eternity, which muſt needs be the only true God.</p>
               <p>But ſome men may ſay, how can the Holy Spirit be God, ſeeing Chriſt ſaith, <hi>that he will pray the Father to ſend him,</hi> and when he comes, he ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf; can he be the Meſſenger of the Father, or of Chriſt to bring their minds unto the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of men, and yet be the ſame true and only God.</p>
               <p>For anſwer unto this, you muſt know, that all the mercy that is, or that can be extended unto the ſons of Men, comes unto them through the mediation of the Lord Jeſus; and therefore it was neceſſary that Chriſt ſhould dye, and riſe, and aſcend; yea I muſt tell you if Chriſt had not gone on and finiſhed the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, as well as undertook it. I ſay, if Chriſt ſhould have left the work in the midſt, as his poor Diſciples through their ignorance would have had him, there could never have been ſo great a mercy extended, neither to them, not to any others as the coming of the Holy Spirit, and therefore our Lord tells them, he muſt go, or elſe the Comforter will not come; now the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherefore the Spirit is ſaid to be ſent to do ſo many good
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118935:18"/>Offices for the Saints, is not to make us think that he is an inferior Meſſenger, but to let us know that all that joy and comfort, peace, and ſanctification; and in a word, all that Grace that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended through the Divine operation of the Holy Spirit, it all comes unto us through the blood-ſhedding of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and truly my Brethren, if you do but conſider the work of the Spirit in the hearts of Men; me thinks it is enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you or any knowing men in the world, that he that doth it muſt needs be God. If a man be but an experienced man, and doth but mind the great blindneſs that is in the mind, and the hardneſs that is in the heart, and doth but conſider how the ſoul is in ſlaved under the power of ſin and Sathan, living in the love and ſervice of Wickedneſs, being alienated from the life of God, being far from the fear and love of him, having no delight in his Commandements, but being ungodly and graceleſs, dead in tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſſes and ſins; and then on the other hand conſiders what an Eſtate the ſoul muſt be brought unto before it can be fit for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal communion with God. If a perſon do but thus mind the greatneſs of the work the Spirit is to do, in taking away the filth and pollution of the heart, and cleanſing the whole man from all <hi>filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit,</hi> and the renuing of the ſoul in <hi>knowledg and holineſs,</hi> and making it meet to be a <hi>partaker of the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Saints in light.</hi> Now I ſay, what man that hath Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and faſted, and watched, and uſed all the means he can, and yet finds in what a frame his heart continueth, how far from that purity, and God-like-neſs that one day he hopeth to enjoy; but now which way could a man expect it, if he that had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken the work were not infinite in Power, Wiſdom, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for my part I look upon this work as the greateſt of all thoſe wonderful works that God hath done, or hath promiſed to do, and therefore it is not likely that the greateſt of all works ſhould be laid upon the ſhoulders of him that is leſs than God.</p>
               <p>Again, if you look <hi>Pſalm</hi> 139. there you ſhall find that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet aſcribes both Omni-preſence and the ſearching of the heart unto the Holy Spirit, which plainly ſpeaks out his being God, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 9 1. you find <hi>Paul</hi> calling the Holy Ghoſt to bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the truth of his heart, ſorrow for his Brethren the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> which plainly proves that he is God. See two Texts for this,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118935:19"/>1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.39. <hi>For thou, even thou only knoweſt the hearts of the children of men;</hi> the ſame words you have in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.30. in both which places you ſee it is the peculiar prerogative of the only true God, to know the hearts of the ſons of men; and I think no man is, or at leaſt ſhould be ſo weak, as to think the Apoſtle would call him to bear witneſs of the truth of the heart, that doth not underſtand and know the heart. I ſhall name you but one Text more for this, and that is <hi>Luke</hi> 1.35. <hi>And the Angel an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and ſaid unto her, the Holy Ghoſt ſhall come upon thee, and the power of the Higheſt ſhall overſhadow thee: therefore alſo that holy thing which ſhall be born of thee, ſhall be called the Son of God.</hi> Here you ſee that the Holy Spirit is called the higheſt, and I think a title beyond this is not given any where, nor cannot be given to the only true God: but beſides, the Angel tells <hi>Mary</hi> that the Holy Ghoſt ſhall come upon her, and by the power of him ſhe ſhould conceive, and therefore this Son of hers ſhould be called the Son of God. Now therefore me thinks this ſhould put the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs beyond all diſpute; for if the Holy Spirit be the Father of our Lord Jeſus, ſure he cannot be leſs than the only true God.</p>
               <p>But it may be you will ſay unto me, How ſhall all this that I have ſaid be reconciled? Can the Father be God, and the Son be God, and the Holy Spirit be God, and yet there be but one only true God?</p>
               <p>Beloved, I pray you do not caſt away an Opinion becauſe it is old, neither do I perſwade you to receive it therefore, but mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure all Opinions both old and new by the meaſuring line of Truth, the Word of God, unto which I ſhall leave you for the tryal of this great myſtery of godlineſs, and ſhall commend two Texts more unto you for the reconciling of what hath been ſaid, the one is in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Great is the myſterie of godlineſs, God was manifeſt in the fleſh.</hi> Here me thinks the Apoſtle ſhews you how all this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable, <hi>God was manifeſt in the fleſh,</hi> ſaith he, not the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Chriſt without the Father, and without the Spirit; but God ſaith, <hi>He was manifeſted in the fleſh,</hi> that is the God-head, as it is written, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.30. <hi>I and my Father are one,</hi> not only in communion as ſome may think, but alſo in union and One-neſs, as it is plain, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14 9, 10, 11. another Text you have in <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3, 9. <hi>In whom</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt, <hi>are hid all the treaſures of wiſdom and knowledg.</hi> Mark it I pray you, if all the treaſures of Wiſdom and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118935:19"/>Knowledg be hid in Chriſt, then are you like to find none of them out of him; but all the wiſdom of the Father, and of the Spirit it will be all found in Chriſt, as it followeth here in <hi>verſe</hi> 9. <hi>For in him dwelleth all the fulneſs of the God head bodily.</hi> I know not how you can have more expreſs and plain words; all the fulneſs of the Father and of the Spirit, if that be the fulneſs of the God-head you ſee dwells in Chriſt; that is, it hath ſuch a real union, an One-neſs with the humane nature of the Lord Jeſus, that in <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. his Blood is there called the <hi>Blood of God.</hi> I ſhall leave theſe Texts of Scriptures to your ſerious conſideration, and proceed no further at this time, but leave the <hi>Application</hi> till the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="exercise">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:118935:20"/>
               <head>THE FIFTH EXERCISE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 17.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>This is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>I Have in the morning from theſe words, as you know opened the Doctrine of the God-head unto you, a work which I have not been forward in, nor ſhould I have medled with it, being a work of an high nature, and requireth the beſt abilities that theſe times do afford; but only for theſe reaſons I have now done it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I find ſome ſuch motions flying abroad both in diſcourſe and in print about this ſubject, which in my judgement ſavours not well.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I do not find able men, men of knowledg, ſuch as I would be glad to provoke to this work, ſo forward to bring forth light, as others to bring forth darkneſs, and if they have, it is more than I know.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the matter I have ſpoken to, fell in my way, and I thought I might do well, and it was my duty to bring forth my Mite in ſuch a time as this, wherein I find ſo many caſting vails over the Name of Chriſt, and of the Holy Spirit; now therefore I do beſeech you ſeriouſly to conſider of that which hath been ſaid unto you; take heed of looking upon our Lord Jeſus as a meer Creature, leſt your Faith fail you in the day of Temptation; if the work of Redemption be but conſidered how great it is; what a price muſt be laid down before this work could be done: and that Law which in that condition in which man once ſtood, would have been his life; now he cannot expect nothing from it as the caſe ſtandeth, but only death; but all the life and pardoning Grace that now cometh to poor man, comes only through the Blood of the Lord Jeſus; now except a man know the worth and all-ſufficiency of Chriſt, that he is perfectly able to remove all the Curſes which his ſins have deſerved, and alſo able to procure him all the bleſſings his ſoul ſtands in need of; it will be very hard if not altogether impoſſible to reſt upon him in the day of tryal; and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118935:20"/>ſo likewiſe when a man ſhall come to ſee what a great work it is to change the heart of man, to ſubdue ſin, and to ſanctifie the ſoul; and when he ſhall ſee the barrenneſs of his heart in the graces and fruits of the Spirit of Chriſt alſo, and withall conſiders what a degree of perfection all thoſe are brought unto that inherit Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, and then minds that the Spirit of God is he that hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to carry on this hard, and to man, this impoſſible work. If now he be not eſtabliſhed in the knowledg and firm belief of this, that the Holy Spirit that carries on this work, is the only true God; I ſay except a man beleeve, and know this, he can have little ground to hope or beleeve that ever it will come to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but wherefore ſhould any men be ſo hardly brought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve this; me thinks it is for want of conſideration; the ſcriptures you know ſpeaks of the Spirit of God in ſome places, and in other places of the Spirit of Chriſt; ſhould we therefore be ſo weak as to think that the Father hath one Spirit, &amp; Chriſt another? but now if we muſt needs underſtand that the Spirit of God &amp; the Spirit of Chriſt is but one Spirit; wherefore ſhould we not as well believe that God &amp; the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> are all one likewiſe? &amp; then Beloved, if the Spirit of Chriſt and the Father be one, and <hi>God</hi> and the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> one, then wherefore ſhould we think that the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Chriſt and of the Father are more than one; but I ſhall preſs this no further, but come now to make ſome Uſe of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. And if it be ſo that there is one, and but one only true God, who is the fountain and perfection of all Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Truth, and goodneſs, who alone made Heaven and Earth, the ſeas, and all the Hoſts of Creatures, that are contained in them, and on whoſe meet grace and love depends the happineſs and well-being of all things whatſoever, whoſe all ſeeing eye beholds all the ſecrets of all hearts, and whoſe Eternal, inviſible, unchangeable, Almighty, and Omni-preſent Being fills the whole Creation, but is not contained in it, who is worthy of all honour, ſervice, praiſe, and worſhip from all Creatures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more; I ſay if this be ſo, then let this <hi>God</hi> be our <hi>God,</hi> let us have no other but him alone to be our <hi>God.</hi> I ſhall not trouble you nor my ſelf with that fooliſh Generation of men that uſe to pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture him up, and to ſet him forth by ſuch vain Images as their hands can make; I hope you are paſt this abſurd and fooliſh pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, but I pray you beware that you ſet up no. Idols of him in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118935:21"/>your minds. Oh do not ſuffer any thought or imagination of him to come or to reſt within your hearts that is low or carnall, take heed that you do not liken him to any thing that ever your eyes have ſeen, but let your thoughts be of him acording unto that glorious diſcription that his own boly records give of him; let high reverence, and honour, love and holy fear accompany every thought that comes into your minds of his moſt excellent and glorious Name; be ſure you chuſe him for your chiefeſt good, let him be your only Diadem, and the Crown which your hearts have choſen for your chiefeſt treaſure; be ſure that you do not eſteem, love, nor honour, any relation or thing whatſoever, as you do this moſt High and only true God; for if you do, you commit Idolatry againſt him who is a jealous God and will not give his glory to another; and therefore beware, for whatſoever any man doth ſet up and in heart eſteeme, love or honour above God, or equall with him, ſets up another God, and ſhall be reckoned amongſt Idolaters and ſuch as have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſpiritual whoredom againſt him, when Chriſt ſhall come to judg every man according to his works.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall more particularly come to ſhew you ſomething of the honour that is due to this only true God, in ſetting ſome of thoſe duties before you, which in eſpecial you owe to him.</p>
               <p>Firſt then give him this honour, to yeeld up your hearts unto him, to love him above all things whatſoever; this uſe <hi>Moſes</hi> makes of this point, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.45. <hi>hear O Iſrael,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Lord our God is one Lord; and thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy might.</hi> Here you ſee what is due to God even love in the very height of it; the whole heart, ſoul, might, is all little enough for God; no creature muſt come between the heart and God, neither wife nor child, nor pleaſure, nor profit, for if there be any thing in the world, that a man loves better than God, or as well as he; this is no leſs a ſin than the ſetting up of another God; therefore look to your hearts in theſe two ſpecial caſes; when the glory of God comes in competition, either with a mans beloved relations, or his beloved ſins, if he cannot caſt them both away for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his God, he is unworthy of him; ſee I pray you what our Lord Jeſus ſaith to this point, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26. <hi>If any man come to me and hate not his father and mother, wife and children, brethren
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118935:21"/>and ſiſters, yea and his own life alſo, he cannot be my diſciple.</hi> Mark it beloved, here you ſee how far you muſt exceed in your love to God, above the love that you ought to bear to any, even the deareſt thing in the whole world unto you; our Saviour you ſee gives us to know that when Parents or Children, wife or life, the which nothing can be dearer, comes in competition with Chriſt, we muſt be ſo far from loving any of them above the Lord, that we muſt in compariſon of the love we bear to him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, hate them; leſſe cannot be in the words then this much: if ſo be, as if Chriſt ſhould ſay, freinds, when it comes to that, that you cannot enjoy the neer and deareſt thing that you have in the world, upon which your hearts are moſt ſet, without doing ſomething that will be contrary to my will, and glory, rather than you ſhould ſin againſt me or diſhonour my holy Name you ought to forſake them, and caſt them away, as if you did not love them at all, but rather hate them; and all this is to be done through that exceeding love that I look you ſhould bear to me, beyond what you ought to have for all thoſe things that are moſt dear unto you, and may in a meaſure be beloved of you. Thus it ought to be, but I pray you examine how it is, whether you do thus love him or no, or whether there be not ſome relation, or elſe, (which is worſe) ſome vanity, or ſin, that hath ſtolen the greateſt part of your affiections from God; look to your hearts I beſeech you, and take heed that you be not found amongſt thoſe men that are lovers of pleaſures, more then lovers of God, or in ſome other ſuch like ſin; nay ſuppoſe it be a child, or ſome other dear relation, that thou preferreſt before the glory of God, take heed thou pay not as dear for this ſin, as <hi>Eli</hi> did; his ſin was this, that he preferred the honour of his Sons, before the honour of God, and therefore muſt both his Sons fall by the Sword in one day; beſide what fell both upon himſelf and upon his houſe for ever. Mark alſo what <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith to <hi>Aaron</hi> his brother, Levit. 19.3. upon the occaſion of the death of his two ſons, this is it that the Lord hath ſaid, <hi>I will be ſanctified in them that come nigh me, and before all the people I will be glorified.</hi> Which is as much as if <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould ſay, thy ſons have diſhonour'd God, and therefore for the glorifiying of his own Name, he hath out them of; and the text ſaith, that <hi>Aaron held his place;</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby his great reſpect to the honour of God, that if the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118935:22"/>deareſt things he had, were taken away, if it did but make for the glory of God, he had not then one word to ſay; here is a very worthy example, I pray you let us follow it, and if we ſee at any time that any thing that is never ſo dear unto us, muſt be taken away, if it make for the honour and glory of God, yeeld it up with all willingneſs, and be ſure that what ever you give him elſe, give him the heart, for with leſs then that he will not be pleaſed.</p>
               <p>The next duty that I ſhall lay before you, is the fear of God; I pray you conſider what a great deal of reaſon you have to fear this moſt glorious and only true God, and to fear him only, for he it is that can do you good or hurt, he can do either, and none in the World can hinder him; if God undertake to be a mans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, all the world cannot hurt him, although they put forth their utmoſt power, for the Lord will find out a thouſand wayes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver a man from the ſtrongeſt Tyrant in the world: likewiſe if the Lord ſet himſelf againſt a man, there is no delivering of him forth of his hand, all the power and wiſdom in the world cannot do it; therefore ſtand in awe of him, and do not let the fear of man cauſe you to turn out of the way of the Lord; it is much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for to make all the men in the world your enemies, yea even your deareſt Friends and all, rather than God. But I pray you fear him as God, not ſlaviſhly, but as it becomes Children; let the fear and dread of his great Name awe your hearts continually, and remember that it is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God; but withall conſider his love and compaſſions to ſinners, his wiſdom and faithfulneſs as well as his righteouſneſs and power, that your fear of him may be mixed with love to him, and confidence in him, that ſo a child-like reverence, and an humble awe may be continually upon your hearts; and take heed that the fear of man do not ſnare you; remember what <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith to this, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 51 12.13 <hi>Who art thou that thou ſhouldeſt be afraid of a man that ſhall dye? and of the Son of man that ſhall be made as graſs? and forgetteſt the Lord thy Maker that hath ſtretched forth the Heavens, and laid the foundations of the earth;</hi> here you ſee how the Prophet reaſons us out of this ſin. Firſt, he asketh, <hi>Who he is that fears man?</hi> intimating that it is ſome ſtrange Creature, ſome coward or fool, one that hath ſtrangely forgot himſelf, and he ſhews the Reaſon.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:118935:22"/>
               <p> Firſt, the man <hi>ſhall dye that is feared;</hi> and therefore a fooliſh thing to fear him that ſhall neither live to reward him, nor to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he ſhall be made as <hi>graſs;</hi> and what wiſe man would fear ſo vain a thing as graſs, a powerleſs creature that can neither help nor hurt a man.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, and that which makes the ſin very great, is this, that while a man fears man, he forgets God. Now there be three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations more in this thirteenth <hi>verſe,</hi> that ſhould keep up the fear of God in the heart, and ſhould likewiſe keep down the fear of man.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he is our <hi>Maker.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>He ſtretcheth out the Heavens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>He layeth the foundations of the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As if the Prophet ſhould ſay, if a man would conſider the workmanſhip of God, when he looks to the Heavens, or when he looks to the earth, and conſiders the glorious works that God hath done in both; or if a man did but look upon himſelf, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideringly mind how he is made, and who is his Maker, he would never be ſo fooliſh as to ſuffer the fear of man ſo to prevail to the eating out of the fear of God out of the heart, but would walk al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in the fear of him, who is alone to be feared, and meet to be had in ſpecial reverence of all that comes about him.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall proceed to the third duty, and that is dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this only true God. Beloved, there is no other that you can truſt in, but in him you may truſt ſafely; a man can never be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed by trnſting in him, for he is a Rock on whom you may reſt with full aſſurance, all thoſe that truſt in him ſhall never be aſhamed, therefore truſt in him at all times, and for all things that your ſouls ſtand in need of, you may go to him for it not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Prayer, but alſo by dependance, whatever your wants be, whether you want pardoning or purging mercy, or ſanctifying grace, or outward things in all caſes whatſoever, truſt perfectly and fully upon him, without fear for a ſupply of all your wants, for he is the only true God, that is to ſay, he is the fulneſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of all power, wiſdom, mercy, truth, and goodneſs whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and one that can no more diſappoint the ſoul that truſteth in him, than he can ceaſe to be God; but I beſeech you take heed that you truſt in no other perſon nor thing whatſoever, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118935:23"/>in him, for if you do, you commit Idolatry againſt him, therefore ſet up no other gods to your ſelves; I pray you ſee what the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith to this caſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Curſed be the man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arm, and whoſe heart departeth from the Lord;</hi> here you may ſee how this ſin is curſed of truſting in man; it would make one tremble to fall under the curſe of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; what is the matter that procureth this Curſe? why, the ſin is truſting in man, and that is a very grievous ſin, for it is a making fleſh his arm, that is, his ſtrength; and that is to ſet up another god, as you may ſee in the words following, <hi>and whoſe heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth from the Lord;</hi> mark it I pray you, when a man depends upon the Creature for any thing that is proper for God to give; this is to aſcribe that to the Creature which is due to God, and it is a very high degree of ſin to depart from the Lord, and that in heart, and to reſt upon the Creature for help inſtead of <hi>God,</hi> it is plainly to deny him, and to honour the Crearure, and that in heart with the greateſt honour that can be given to the Lord: for it is to acknowledg the Creature to have both power and mercy to help in time of need, and to deny it to be found in <hi>God,</hi> ſee <hi>Pſalm</hi> 62.10, 11, 12. <hi>If riches encreaſe, ſet not your hearts upon them;</hi> but what if we ſhould, wherein lies the ſin? note it I pray you, the ſin is great, and lies in this, that a man ſaith in his heart, there is both power and mercy in Riches to help me; and this ſaith the Prophet only belongeth unto <hi>God,</hi> as it followeth in the next words: Now therefore I pray you truſt in nothing but in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>God,</hi> neither for ſpiritual nor for temporal things; Oh I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend neither upon Friends nor Riches, no nor yet upon wiſdom, nor ſtrength nor trade, nor any thing in the world that is below the only true <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But you will ſay, what is it to truſt in theſe things, I would not willingly do it, for I know it is a ſin.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, when a man promiſeth himſelf comfort from any thing whatſoever, he truſteth in it, let him ſay what he will to the contrary; as for example, when a man thinketh thus in his heart, I have a Friend that will not ſee me want, or I have a good Trade, or ſo much Riches or Land, therefore it ſhall go well with me, this man truſteth in theſe things; or whoſoever promiſeth himſelf Bread to eat, or Clothes to put on, from any other ground ſave only this, the power, mercy, and truth of <hi>God,</hi> he having un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118935:23"/>to provide for him, truſteth in that thing whatever it is: therefore let Rich men eſpecially remember <hi>Pauls</hi> charge in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17. and look well to their hearts that they do not truſt in their Riches, no not for Bread for to morrow, but only in the promiſes of the living and only true <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth duty that you owe to this only true <hi>God,</hi> is obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; this uſe <hi>Moſes</hi> makes of this point, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.39.40. the Lord ſaith, he <hi>s God both in Heaven and in earth, there is none elſe;</hi> and what follows. <hi>Thou ſhalt keep therefore his ſtatutes, and his Commandements:</hi> I pray you obſerve it, his Commandements muſt be obeyed, that is, all of them you muſt obey, for if you ſhould obey ſome of them, and leave the reſt undone, the Lord would never take it well at your hands; no Beloved, you muſt give up your ſelves to walk univerſally obedient unto all the Commandements, <hi>He that ſhall break one of the leaſt of them</hi> Mat. 5.19. <hi>ſhall be called the leaſt in the kingdom of Heaven,</hi> (that is) that ſhall allowedly and wilfully break the leaſt of them. <hi>God</hi> looks to be obeyed in all things, whatſoever you know to be a duty, although it be never ſo ſmall, or never ſo contemptible, you muſt yeild obedience to it, or whatever you can come to know to be a duty hereafter; you muſt have your hearts in a ready frame to obey when you do come to know, or can come to know more; or whatever you know or can come to know to be a ſin, you muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void and mortifie; there muſt be no bearing with any ſin, no nor with any corruption, if it bring never ſo much profit, or never ſo much pleaſure, all muſt be caſt away that is contrary to his moſt holy will, and all this is to be done willingly, or elſe the Lord accepteth it not, the Lord looks for the whole heart, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you do dot willingly and in love to <hi>God,</hi> yeild up your ſelves to live to him in all things, he will not account it ſincere obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. And as you muſt take heed you obey no ſin, ſo likewiſe you muſt obey no Creature but in the Lord; therefore if the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, or thy Husband, Maſter, or Father, Landlord, or whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever commandeth thee to do any thing that is not according to the will of <hi>God,</hi> let this be an everlaſting Law to thee, in all ſuch caſes obey <hi>God</hi> rather than men; but if any that hath authority over thee ſhall command any thing which is lawful, and may be done without ſcruple of Conſcience: in all ſuch caſes thou art to yeild ready and willing obedience unto them as unto Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118935:24"/>
               <p> And the laſt, but not the leaſt duty that I ſhall now preſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you is this; Take heed that you learn of no man or men what worſhip you muſt give unto God, nor after what manner it muſt be performed; but learn all this of the Lord himſelf, get a ground from the Scriptures for all the Doctrines that you receive for truth. I ſay, get a ground for them in your own underſtandings, and all the wo ſhip of God both for matter and manner, and all the circumſtances thereof; ſee that it be grounded upon the word of truth; if you would be ſure not to commit Idolatry, then take heed of being lead by the judgements of men in any of theſe things; neither do you follow the imaginations of your own hearts in theſe things, but labour to get a diſtinct underſtanding in your own ſouls of whatſoever is to be beleeved for Doctrine, or for whatſoever is to be practiſed in matters of worſhip, for if you walk in darkneſs, you will walk uncomfortably, but if you walk in the light and knowledg of his will, your walking wil both pleaſe him, and bring much comfort and peace to your own Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. But I ſhall now ſpeak one word to provoke thoſe wretched man thet live without God in the world, to conſider of their condition, and ſo conclude. I beſeech you my dear friends do not live ſtill ſo eſtranged from the life of <hi>God;</hi> neither do you go on to abuſe his mercy and loving-kindneſs from day to day as you have done; but let the goodneſs and long-ſuffering of the Lord lead you to Repentance; you have heard what a <hi>God</hi> of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, power. wiſdom, goodneſs, and faithfulneſs he is, yea what an eternal, unchangeable, inviſible, infinite Being he is; you have heard ſomething both of his Name and of his Works, and much more is to be known, and may be known of him in the Word of Truth, and will you continue ſo unthankful and ungodly, abuſing this grace and love of <hi>God,</hi> who hath manifeſted himſelf in his holy Word, that you might come to the knowledg of him, and ſo to ſalvation, and do not you think it a moſt grievous ſin to live as many of you do, as void of the knowledg of him, as thoſe that never heard of his written Word; it is a moſt unthankful abuſe of his goodneſs. O where would ſuch men be glad to hide themſelves at the great Day, even under a Rock, if they did know how to get under it; and as for many of thoſe that cannot chuſe but know ſomething of <hi>God,</hi> how unanſwerable to that little knowledg that they have
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118935:24"/>do they walk, neither loving nor fearing his great Name, having no reſpect at all to his worſhip, nor to any of his Commandements, nor truſting in him at all, no more than if he had never made them any promiſes. Beloved, how evident be theſe things, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all that God hath made known of himſelf unto men? yet how little love have they for him? and how little zeal for his glory, loving pleaſure, profit, yea ſin it ſelf better than <hi>God,</hi> fearing the frowns of men more than the diſpleaſure of him; and truſting in the promiſes of their honeſt Neighbours, yea in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle durty wealth, or any vanity in the world rather than in the power and truth of God, caſting his worſhip and Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments behind their backs, as if they owed him no ſervice; now I pray you bethink your ſelves how you ſhall appear before the Lord at the great Day, and how he will take it at your hands, that you ſhould live ſo prophane a life, being alienated from the life of God, and rooted and hardened in all wickedneſs, as if you had never known nor heard of the Name of God; Oh, Repent in time, and thankfully imbrace that means of grace which <hi>God</hi> in the riches of his mercy doth yet afford unto you; and ſo much I ſhall commend to your conſideration, and to the bleſſing of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118935:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:118935:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="exercise">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:118935:26"/>
               <head>THE SIXTH EXERCISE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 17.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And this is life eternal, that they might know thee, the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>I Shall now come to ſpeak to this third and laſt general Head in this Text, namely, the Lords ſending of Jeſus Chriſt; and for this end and purpoſe, that I may proceed both with brevity and plainneſs; I ſhall proceed in this order.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I ſhall ſhew you the excellency of the perſon of Chriſt, even as he is the Son.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I ſhall clear it unto you by the Scriptures, how that Jeſus Chriſt had a Being with the Father in glory before the world was, and from thence was ſent into the world to take upon him our Nature.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I ſhall endeavour to ſet before you the ends of his coming into the world.</p>
               <p>And now for the firſt of theſe, I pray you take notice that the Scriptures in many places do exalt the Lord Jeſus above all other Creatures whatſoever; I ſhall name you ſome few of them: look <hi>Hebrews</hi> 1. the whole Chapter, but eſpecially note two or three paſſages in the beginning, he is there ſaid to be <hi>appointed heir of all things,</hi> and to be the <hi>brightneſs of his Fathers glory;</hi> and to be made <hi>much better then the Angels:</hi> which word <hi>made better,</hi> muſt needs have reſpect to his Creature-nature: alſo he is there ſaid to be <hi>him, by whom God did make all things, and doth uphold them.</hi> And in the Revelations 3.14. he is called <hi>the beginning of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God;</hi> and in <hi>Col.</hi> 1.15, 16, 17. he is called <hi>the firſt-born of every Creature;</hi> &amp; all things are ſaid <hi>to be created by him, and for him,</hi> and he to be <hi>before them;</hi> &amp; that by him <hi>they all conſiſt.</hi> So that from theſe and other like Texts I gather, that God did firſt create the Spirit of Chriſt, &amp; filled him with his own glory, and then by him brought forth the whole creation; I ſay that Spirit of Chriſt, which afterward
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118935:26"/>took fleſh of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and ſo became true man, was the firſt and the choiceſt piece of all the workman-ſhip of God; for you muſt know that Chriſt had a created Spirit that was ſet up, and brought forth, and brought up with the Lord, and was by him before any of his other works had a Being, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.22. to the 30. and this is he that <hi>the Lord poſſeſſed in the beginning of his way,</hi> and is the ſame that talked with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> made interceſſion to for <hi>Sodom, Gen.</hi> 18. and that brought the <hi>children of Iſrael through the wilderneſs;</hi> and is the ſame that God commandeth them to obey, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
               <p>But this I ſhall ſay no more to now, but come to the ſecond particular; and that is, to ſhew you that the Lord Chriſt was ſent from the boſom of the Father into the world, for us; you will ſee this plain in many places, I wil name you ſome of them, John 3, 13. <hi>No man hath aſcended up to heaven, but he that came down from heaven, even the Son of man.</hi> The words are very plain; <hi>the ſon of man,</hi> you ſee came down from heaven, and in the 31. ver. <hi>He that cometh down from heaven is above all; he that is of the earth is earthly, and ſpeaketh of the earth, he that cometh from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is above all.</hi> I pray you mark it, Chriſt is here oppoſed to all other men in this, that they are from the earth, but he is from heaven; yea as he is the ſon of man, he is from heaven; but if he had received his firſt beginning in the womb of the Virgin, as well in reſpect of his ſpirit as in reſpect of his body, he could no more have been ſaid to have been ſent from heaven, but muſt have been as truly of the earth, as he is man, as all other men be; but it is very plain that the man-hood of Chriſt is from heaven, as you may ſee alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47. <hi>The ſecond man is the Lord from heaven;</hi> the owrds be ſo plain that I need not urge them; look alſo John 6.38. <hi>For I came down from heaven, not to do mine own will, but the will of him that ſent me.</hi> Note it I pray you, as he is God he doth his own will, but he came down from heaven, and yet not to do his own will, therefore he ſpeaks here as man, it is clear; and ſo in the 62 verſes. <hi>What and if ye ſhall ſee the ſon of man aſcend up where he was before?</hi> How evident is this, that the ſon of man was in heaven before, and was ſent from thence into the world: and Iohn 16.28. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I came forth from the Father, and am come into the world; again I leave the world and go to the Father;</hi> and in this ſame <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.5. how earneſtly doth our
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118935:27"/>Lord pray the Father, to let him enjoy that ſame <hi>glory that he had with him before the world was.</hi> Now it is very clear this he did not now enjoy at this time that glory that he had enjoyed before the world was; and this is now earneſtly expected and prayed for, as you ſee; a caſe incedent to the man-hood of Chriſt; but it is that which can never befall the God-head, for there is nothing more obſurd and ſenſeleſs, than for a man to think that the God-head can ever be deprived of the full enjoyment of it ſelf; now that he took upon him our nature is plain, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16. and many other places might be aledged to prove this if need were.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall now come to the third particular, to ſhew you the ends of our Lords coming into the world; and the firſt end of his coming, is to teach us the will of his Father, and to manifeſt his great love to the ſons of men, according to that promiſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.15, 18, 19. and <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22. and 7.37. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16, 17. and 12, 16. to the end.</p>
               <p>Secondly he came to be the true High-Prieſt, of which all the other were types, and to offer up himſelf for ſinners, and to bear all there infirmities, according as that whole epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> witneſſeth, and many other places alſo might be aledged to prove it if it were needful.</p>
               <p>Thirdly Chriſt came to reign over all men, yea to reign in the conſciences of men, and hath power of judging and condemning all thoſe that be found diſobedient unto him, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2.8. to the end, <hi>Luke</hi> 19, 14, 27. <hi>Romans</hi> 14.9. and 15.12. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.22, 23, 27, 29, 30. But I ſhall take a little time more particularly to open ſome of theſe things unto you, and to ſhew you what a ſweet advantage we have by the coming of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Firſt he came to redeem us from the curſe of the Law, and hath born the curſe for us; and by this means will deliver all the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> from the miſery that the firſt ſin brought upon them, yea and from the curſes of the Law in general; even from the paws of death it ſelf, and from all the miſeries that procure it, ſo that the ungodlieſt of men, ſhall riſe again from the dead; and thus farr he is the Saviour of all men, what ever he doth more for them, and if they periſh eternally, it is for ſinning againſt the Goſpel, either for neglecting their own ſalvation, or for turning
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118935:27"/>the grace of God into wantonneſs, or for ſome ſuch-like evills as theſe be. Now I beſeech you conſider by what means Chriſt is thus a Saviour to you; Beloved, it is by bearing the Curſe for you, and undergoing thoſe miſeries that are due to you for your offences, by his poverty you are rich, by his ſtripes we are heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by his ſorrows we have joy, and by his death we have life; <hi>He was made ſin for us, though in himſelf he knew no ſin, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him;</hi> although in our ſelves we are unrighteous; alſo Jeſus Chriſt hath by his Blood and ſufferings for the ſons of men purchaſed a juſt authority and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over them all; ſo that if they refuſe to come unto him, and when light comes, chuſe darkneſs rather, and when he calls them to Repent and beleeve the Goſpel, and ſayes, look to me, and be ye ſaved all ye the ends of the earth; if then I ſay, they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to come unto him for life, yet ſhall they never be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to come before his Judgement-ſeat, to receive the juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of that diſobedience: but on the other hand the Lord Jeſus came to be a Saviour to all thoſe that come unto him, yea that when he calls refuſe, not to hear, but are willing to ſuffer the reproofs of wiſdom to enter into their ſouls, yea he will ſave all theſe with an everlaſting ſalvation. Beloved, he came to bring ſalvation to ſuch in all the parts of it. Firſt, he juſtifieth ſuch from all that from which they could not be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> yea he hath power to forgive ſins, and he will juſtifie them freely through the work of Redemption. But further, I pray you obſerve the Lord Jeſus will give Repentance to, and graciouſly melt and ſoften the hearts of poor ſinners; if they do but hearken to his voice, it is the very end of his coming, to give Repentance as well as Remiſſion of ſins, and he will work your hearts to Repentance if you do not oppoſe the work of his grace, and continue to do it; yea although you have hearts never ſo hard, he will ſoften them himſelf by his own Spirit; if you do not harden your own beares, but wait at wiſdoms gate, then ſhall you ſee how graciouſly he will manifeſt himſelf at laſt; indeed if ſo be that a ſoul were to work Repentance in his own heart, or muſt ſee that it is wrought there before he might either go for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or had a ground to expect it, that were enough to break the heart indeed, and to diſcourage a man for ever hoping after mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; but the caſe is far otherwiſe, for Chriſt came to work Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118935:28"/>and to ſeek and ſave that which was loſt, and therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a perſon be never ſo hard-hearted and unbelieving; and although he be never ſo dead, if he have never a ſpark of life in him, if he will but hearken to the voice of Chriſt, Chriſt will give him life; again, another work that Chriſt came to do, is to ſubdue ſin, and although it be never ſo ſtrong, he will ſubdue it: it can never be too ſtrong for him; when a poor ſoul looks about him, and ſees a multitude of ſtrong corruptions within him, and then looks again, and ſees another multitude of ſtrong temptations and ſnares without him, round about, and withall diſcerns the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his own heart, and ſees how eaſily he is tempted, finding his own heart alwayes ready to betray him into the Tempters hands: this is indeed enough to work amazing thoughts, and to drive a perſon to utter deſpair; if it were not for that ground of hope we have in Jeſus Chriſt; but here is a ſtrong ground of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence in this, that Chriſt hath undertaken to ſave men from ſin, and to ſubdue it, and that he hath provided weapons to pull down Sathans ſtrongeſt holds, and to bring under every luſt, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſtrong and high; ſo that there ſhall not be an imagination or a thought, but Chriſt can and will conquer, and bring into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection by the power of his Spirit, yea his buſineſs into the world was to purge the Conſcience from dead works, and to cleanſe and purifie the ſoul from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, and to purge us from our very Idols. Now therefore conſider how great the goodneſs of God is, to put this work into the hands of Chriſt; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſs, if it had been left in our hands it would never have been done, but he hath undertaken it himſelf, and therefore it will proſper. Again, another end of our Lord Jeſus his coming into the world is to comunicate the graces of his Spirit to all that come to him for them, <hi>John</hi> 1.16. and <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. <hi>How much more ſhall your heavenly Father give the Holy Spirit to them that ask him,</hi> ſaith the Text; here you ſee upon what terms you may obtain the Holy Spirit, it is but going to Chriſt to ask it, he hath promiſed it, and he cannot deny it, for he is truth it ſelf, and cannot deny himſelf, it is impoſſible. Again, Jeſus Chriſt came to bring life and immortality to light through the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. Mark it I pray you, his coming hath brought <hi>life and immortality,</hi> that is as much as to ſay, he hath brought an immortal crown of life and glory; yea may ſome poor ſoul ſay, it is a good portion indeed,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:118935:28"/>if a man knew which way to come to inherit it, but alaſs, I do not know which way I can come by this bleſſed inheritance; that is anſwered in the next words, he hath brought it to light through the Goſpel, that is as much as if he ſhould ſay, he came alſo to bring a Goſpel that ſhould bring light with it unto the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings and ſouls of men. Beloved, it is not promiſed to men whether they attend to the Goſpel or no; therefore deceive not your own hearts, but if you do attend on the Goſpel, and take its direction, it will bring that light into thy ſoul that will bring thee to ſee how to come to enjoy this bleſſed inheritance; there be many precious promiſes of the like nature in the Scriptures, look <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.6 firſt verſes, and do but conſider them, there is a plain promiſe that if you uſe the ſame diligence in praying and ſeeking for this ſpiritual riches, as men uſe to do for temporal Riches, you ſhall be ſure to find it; and the ground of this is; becauſe that out of the mouth of the Lord cometh knowledg and underſtanding; it is not therefore becauſe a man makes diligent ſearch, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth it, no, nor yet becauſe it lyeth either in his diligence, or the Ordinances unavoidably, but becauſe the grace and love of God is ſuch, that he ſent Jeſus Chriſt for that very end, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever would be but perſwaded to wait upon him in the uſe of the means appointed by him for that end and purpoſe, ſhould not miſs of that grace and ſweet advantage to his poor ſoul; another end of his coming is, to tread down Sathan under our feet, ſo that although he be full of ſubtilty, and craft, and ſtrength, and makes uſe of all the means and inſtruments he can, yet ſhall he never be too hard for that ſoul that comes to Chriſt for Refuge, no, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the poor ſoul be laden with ignorance, luſt, hardneſs of heart, and unbelief too, and never ſo many ſinful and ſoul-deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſeaſes, if he do but come to Chriſt in good earneſt, and deſire him to deliver him, he wil certainly do it; nay if when Chriſt knocks at the door of a ſinners heart to bid him ſtand up from the dead, and he will deliver him out of the paw of the Devil; if then I ſay you ſhut not Chriſt out of door, and bid him depart from thee, and tell him thou deſireſt not the knowledg of his wayes. I ſay again; if thou deal not thus with him, it is the proper work for which Chriſt came to ſeek out loſt ſinners, and to ſave them, and therefore he will not be wanting to do it; again, he came to be a fellow-feeler of our infirmities, that he might know what it
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118935:29"/>is to ſuffer adverſity, and to be tempted, to the end he might be a merciful High Prieſt, and might miniſter that help, comfort, and ſtrength which would be needful upon all occaſion, &amp; therefore you may be ſure that whatever your ſouls diſtreſs is, whether it be ſin, ſorrow, temptation, or of what kind ſoever, there is help for you in Chriſt, if you do not neglect it or refuſe it; but you muſt know alſo that Chriſt came to command ſinners to Repent and Beleeve, and obey him, and if you ſhall for the love of pleaſure, or profit, wilfully refuſe the offers of his Grace, you muſt know he came with Authority to execute judgement in all ſuch caſes; and thus much for this preſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="exercise">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:118935:29"/>
               <head>THE SEVENTH EXERCISE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 17.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>This is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>YOu know that in the morning I came to ſpeak to this third general head of Doctrine in the Text, namely, the ſending of Jeſus Chriſt; and I have ſhewed you who ſent him, and from whence he came, and what he was ſent to do; all that I ſhall now add to that I have ſaid already, is only this: that as the Father hath ſent him to take upon him theſe three great Offices, King, Prieſt, and Prophet, ſo he hath furniſhed him with power and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to do all the work that doth belong unto theſe Offices; therefore you need not fear to caſt your burthen upon the Lord, for God hath laid help upon one that is mighty, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 89.19. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.1. one ſtrong enough to break down the power of all your enemies, ſin, luſt, ſnare, temptation, or whatever elſe lies in the way of your peace, he is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all that come unto God by him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7 25.</p>
               <p>Now the reaſon of this, wherefore it was neceſſary for Chriſt to be ſent of the Father for the doing of this great work, is this: ſuch is the helpleſneſs of poor fallen man, he is ſo dead in Treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſins, and in ſo miſerable and loſt a condition, that nothing but the free Grace of God in Chriſt can poſſibly help him; for he in himſelf is ſo utterly unworthy of any mercy, that there is no other way to bring him into acceptation with God, but only through the worthineſs of the Lord Jeſus. Again, there is that weakneſs in poor man that he is no way able to help himſelf; he can neither repent, beleeve, nor obey, no nor get any Grace into his own heart, nor mortifie any Corruption, nor of himſelf find out the way by which any of all theſe great works ſhould be done; but for ought that he can do for himſelf, he is in a neceſſity of periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118935:30"/>for ever; there is no help for him, but only in Jeſus Chriſt; and if the Lord had not in the riches of his free Grace provided ſuch a Mediator as was able to ſave to the uttermoſt, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful man had never been recovered; and therefore the Father ſent him that was fully able both to juſtifie, and to ſanctifie, to open the blind eyes, and to purge the Conſcience, and in a word, to lay the firſt and the laſt ſtone in the building of Salvation; and if God would any way ſhew his love to poor loſt fallen man, then muſt he take this courſe, for there was no other way to do it; let us now come to make ſome uſe of this Point.</p>
               <p>And in the firſt place, let it ſerve to provoke the very worſt and wickedeſt of ſinners to come to Chriſt for help and deliverance. Beloved, you have heard what a Saviour he is, therefore I beſeech you do not ſtand to diſpute your own badneſs, but how bad ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you be, caſt your ſelves upon him for help; and to that end that this work may be done throughly, and as it ought to be done, labour in the firſt place to know the worſt of your own hearts, there is many a poor Soul that is afraid to think the worſt of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for fear he ſhould ſee ſo much badneſs as ſhould take off his hopes, and diſcourage him for going to Chriſt for mercy. But I pray you learn to be wiſer than ſo, ſearch your hearts to the very bottom, and how bad ſoever that thou findeſt it, yet be ſure that thou doſt not fail to go to Chriſt for a cure, although thou haſt been never ſo bad, worſe than <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> or any wretch that ever thou readeſt of, or ever heardeſt of; if thou findeſt thy ſelf upon due ſearch to be the verieſt Hypocrite, or the verieſt enemy to <hi>God</hi> and godlineſs that is in the whole world; yet let it not keep thee from going to Chriſt, but make ſo much the more haſt by how much thou findeſt thy ſelf the more wicked; and although thy ſins be never ſo great and never ſo many, there is no ſin but he can par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, yea and he will pardon it if thou come unto him. I ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, there is no ſin nor ſinners, if they come to Chriſt, but he will ſurely be gracious unto them, <hi>He that comes to me will I in no wiſe caſt out,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>John</hi> 6.37. therefore go unto him, and be aſſured he will receive you; whatever your Souls diſeaſes be, ſear not to go unto him with them, for he cures all that come unto him; ſee what woful diſeaſes Chriſt was ſent to cure, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, becauſe he hath anointed me to preach the Goſpel to the poor, he hath ſent me to heal the broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118935:30"/>to preach deliverance to the captives, and recovering of ſight to the blind, to ſet at liberty them that are bruiſed.</hi> Now I pray you let us a little conſider of this text; <hi>he hath anointed me to preach the Goſpel;</hi> and what is the Goſpel? why the Goſpel is free mercy through the blood of Chriſt, pardon, regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſalvation, yea all the happneſs that comes to a ſoul by Jeſus Chriſt, this is the Goſpel, and this Chriſt was anointed to preach, and therefore doing it by the ſpirit, it muſt needs be truth that he preacheth; other men may preach lies, but ſo doth not the fountain of truth, you may be ſure. But who is all this mercy to be preached to? ſaith Chriſt, it is to be preached to the poor; and who is poor? a man is not accounted poor if he have either land or goods, or mony; and ſo it is in ſpiritual things alſo, one altogether deſtitude of whatſoever might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him to God, one that hath no purity neither in heart, nor life, no faith, no love, no knowledg, no mortification, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of mind, no delight in God nor his word, nor having the light of his countenance ſhining upon the ſoul; now one that hath none of all this ſpiritual riches, he is poor; but he that is inriched with any of theſe ſpiritual bleſſings in heavenly things in Chriſt, is not poor: now I hope you ſee who Chriſt was anointed with the ſpirit to teach the Goſpel to; but ſee what follows in the next words, <hi>to heal the broken hearted,</hi> ſaith he, and who is that? why one that hides his head for debt, and owes more then he is worth, this man we account a broken man. So likewiſe when a man is through the ſight of his undone condition, afraid of Arreſts, and executions from God dayly, and knows not where to hide his head, being in fear and anguiſh of ſpirit. Chriſt was ſent you ſee to heal this ſpiritually broken eſtate.</p>
               <p>In the next place, he came to preach deliverance to the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; and this is a worſe degree of evil, when a man is the divils priſoner, taken and kept in his ſnare, this is a very ſad condition indeed, when a man can do nothing, but as the devil his keeper will give him leave; how can his condition be worſe except he were in hell? and yet if ſuch a man will but hearken to the word of Chriſt, he ſhall be ſure to be delivered: yea but my caſe is worſe then all this, may ſome poor ſoul ſay, for I am not only the divels priſoner, but I have given my ſelf up ſo to his will, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:118935:31"/>ſuffered him ſo to blind mine underſtanding, that now if Chriſt ſhould come and throw open the priſon doors, yet ſhall I never find my way out. Yea ſaith Chriſt, in the next words, but I came to open the <hi>blind eyes</hi> alſo; and although the divell have put them quite out, yet ſuffer me to put but ſome ſpitle and clay upon them, and I will recover them again; take but my direction, turn at my reproof, at left do not deſpiſe it, and ſet it at nought, and then be ſure, I will poure out my ſpirit, and that will fully cure thee.</p>
               <p>Yea, but the ſoul may further object and ſay, I have waited on the Ordinances, and endeavoured to get out of the ſnare of the divel, and he hath fetcht me back and beaten me ſore, when I have but aſſeyed to get from him; ſo that I ſee the more I ſtrive the worſe I am bruiſed, and therefore there is no hope for me; yes ſaith Chriſt, I came to ſet at liberty ſuch bruiſed ones, and to preach the acceptable year of the Lord, as it follows in the next words; and although thou haſt waited years and been bruiſed by Satan, yet be ſure the year of Jubile will come when the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſhall ſound for the diliverance of ſuch bruiſed captives as thou art. See one text more, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 57.17, 18. <hi>For the iniquity of his covetouſneſs was I wroth, ſaith God.</hi> And I ſhewed it to, <hi>for I ſmote him,</hi> ſaith he. Yea but it is like it was but a very geritle ſtroke, for if he had ſmitten hard it is like the man would have repented and turned; yes ſaith the Lord, but I did ſtrike hard, for I hid me and was wrath, that is a great blow indeed, beloved, when the Lord hides himſelf that takes away all comfort, and all hope; ſure the ſinner will turn now or never, there will be ſome fruit now of this ſtroke, or elſe he will be given up as one incureable; no ſaith the text, <hi>he went on frowardly,</hi> for all that; and how does God deal with this wicked wretch, now will he not throw him to hell immediately? or if he ſpare him any longer, ſure it is but for diſtruction, that will be the end of him. No ſaith God; <hi>I have ſeen his wayes and will heal him, I will lead him alſo, and reſtore comforts unto him.</hi> Who would look to hear ſuch gracious words as theſe from God? Oh the riches of his free grace, and mercy, to old froward wetched ſinners; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fear not to caſt your ſelves upon him, although you be never ſo bad; but if you be not able to caſt yourſelves upon him, yet do not run away from him, but lie at the Pool, I mean the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118935:31"/>Ordinances, and wait on Chriſt, and he will find a time to viſit you and to heal you; and although you be ſo loſt that you cannot return to him, yet be ſure you hide not your ſelves from him; and then be ſure Chriſt will not fail to do that good work for which his father ſent him, namely; to ſeek and to ſave ſuch loſt ones as thou art.</p>
               <p>And in the next place, labour to beleeve the promiſes, ſir down and conſider how many precious promiſes there be made in the Scriptures to ſinners, to undodly ones, to all the ends of the earth; to all comers, come whoſe will, and whoſoever will, let him come and take <hi>the water of life freely. Revel.</hi> 22.17. <hi>without money or price, as Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 55. that is, without any condition of worth on your part in the leaſt degree, I have laid many precious promiſes before you this day already, read them over again, and ſay to your ſelves, theſe promiſes are held out to me, and to ſuch as I am, and it is my duty to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve them and to apply them to my ſelf; do this the very firſt work you do, think not to repent and to humble hy ſelf firſt; but before ever thou goeſt about that, labour to beleeve; and be not ſo fooliſh as to think to amend either thy heart or thy wayes, before thou beleeveſt: It is true, I would not go about to perſwade you other-wayes, but that it is your duty to be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and to repent, and to caſt away all your trangreſſions, and to ſtudy to be holy both in body and in ſpirit, and alſo in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; but if you think to do any of all theſe great works before you beleeve, you go about a fooliſh work, that will never proſper, nor come to any thing, for you muſt receive all that grace and power from Chriſt by faith, through which you are inabled to all that is good; and therefore if you would repent, or obey, or get your hearts changed, or your luſts ſubdued, go to Chriſt and reſt upon him for grace to do all theſe duties.</p>
               <p>And in the third place, go to the Lord, and ask repentance of him, and begg a new heart, and what ever elſe thy ſoul ſtands in need of, and tell him how great thy wants be, and what gracious promiſes he hath made to ſinners and pray him to make them good to thy poor ſoul.</p>
               <p>But me thinks I hear ſome poor ſoul ſay, indeed if I were able to pray, it were to be hoped that I might ſpeed, but alaſs I am not able to pray in the ſpirit, and therefore I had as good ſay nothing.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:118935:32"/>
               <p> I anſwer, no more can young Ravens pray in the ſpirit, and yet God heareth their cry, and ſo he doth hear alſo the cryes of wicked men, elſe how came <hi>Manaſeh</hi> out of <hi>Bahylon,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.13. alſo ſuch as are wicked are incouraged to ſeek the Lord, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 55.6, 7. Oh but ſayes the poor ſoul, <hi>the prayer of the wicked is a bominable;</hi> therefore how can I pray? I anſwer, if indeed thou meaneſt to go on in the wickedneſs without any purpoſe or deſire to be better, he will not hear in ſuch a caſe; but if thou go to him to be delivered from ſin, as well as from wrath, he will ſurely hear thy cry and wil help thee. Oh but the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, <hi>that if I regard iniquity in my heart, God will not hear me.</hi> To this I anſwer, if indeed thou do regard iniquity thou muſt not look to be heard; but the queſtion is, what it is to regard ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: now I will tell you, that man that goes to God with a forme of words, and with them thinks to pleaſe him, but hath no deſire at all to ask nor yet to receive any help againſt ſin, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to live and continue in that ſtill, this man regards iniquity; but on the other hand, that man that hath luſts that he cannot maſter, but yet he would be well content if the Lord would be pleaſed to ſubdue them for him, and there is no requeſt that he hath more deſire to be heard in, then in this, that he might be delivered from his beloved ſin; Now this man doth nor regard iniquity, although it may be ſtrong in him; But if he cry to the Lord for help he will ſurely hear his cry, and will ſave him. But if thou judgeſt that thou canſt not pray, yet ask for mercy for all that; there is a ſweet text in the Propheſie of <hi>Hoſeah</hi> 14.2. the Lord tels wicked men there, what they ſhall ſay to him, for you moſt know that this Propheſie was ſent to <hi>Iſrael</hi> in there backſlidden and Idolatrous eſtate, and yet the Lords goodneſs is ſuch, that he perſwades them to return and ſeek for mercy, but he takes it for granted that they cannot pray for it; and therefore he tels them what they ſhall ſay, <hi>take with you words; and ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu hom,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>take away all iniquity, and receive us graciouſly.</hi> Mark it I pray you, if they had had a ſpirit of prayer the Lord need not have bidden them take words to them, and ſay receive us, for where a ſpirit of prayer is, there it helpeth our infirmities, and reacheth us to make requeſt according to the will of God, as it is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26, 27. if we have the ſpirit it will ſufficiently open our minds unto our father, but if we
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118935:32"/>have it not, then let us <hi>take words to us, and ſay, receive us gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly,</hi> for the Lord is full of compaſſion, and will hear the cry of miſery in an <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> Gen. 21.17. and if he will hear it for cold water, he would hear it as well, and as willingly for better things, if he did but cry as earneſtly for them.</p>
               <p>In the fourth place, attend on the ordinances of Chriſt, for there his walk is, and there he will come to ſeek for loſt ones, as well as to viſit his people, and there thou wilt have an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity one time or other, to lay hold on the skirt of his garment; therefore wait on him, and know for thy comfort, that never any did ſo and periſhed; no, no, <hi>they ſhall never be aſhamed that wait far him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the fifth place, whenſoever thou meeteſt with any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the ſpirit of God, make much of it, and cloſe with all the advices it ſhall whiſper into thine ears; take heed of ſlighting or neglecting any of the ſweet breathings of it, but give it enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, and what word ſoever comes home to thine heart, conſider of it ſeriouſly, yea although it may be a reproving, or a wounding word, let it not be neglected, for Chriſt comes both to wound and to heal; and therefore what word or motion ſoever comes from his ſpirit, home to thy conſcience, entertain it thankfully, and walk according to the direction it gives thee, humbly.</p>
               <p>And in the laſt place, be ſure to be alwayes watching over thy heart, and eſpecially againſt thoſe luſts that are moſt apt to carry thee away from God, and be ſure to be found fighting alwayes againſt them; and although thou be not ſtrong enough to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, yet do not give over fighting againſt them, but watch, and pray, hear and read, and apply the promiſes, and the threatnings of the word to thy own ſoul dayly, as thou findeſt there is need, either to comfort or to rebuke thy conſcience, and be aſſured, that although thou be too weak for ſin and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, yet Chriſt is ſtrong enough, and he will take thy part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and will come in at laſt with ſanctifying grace, and purge thy conſcience from dead works, to ſerve the living God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. A ſecond uſe, that is to be made of this point, is this; if ſo be that Chriſt came to be ſuch a Saviour, as to ſave from the guilt of ſin, and from the Power of ſin, to ſanctify the ſoul,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118935:33"/>and to deliver from Sathan, and to bear up a ſoul under troubles, and to deliver out of them alſo; then let all beleevers learn to live upon Chriſt for all theſe things at all times. Beloved, in the uſe of other means forget not to exerciſe faith in the blood of Chriſt; when you go to read, hear, or pray, look to Chriſt by faith, who hath appointed theſe as means to make you partakers of his own image, and what ever your ſouls ſtand in need of, whether pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning or purging mercy, or what grace, counſel, comfort, help, or deliverance ſoever, you ſee a ground to aske in prayer; labour alſo to live upon the free grace of God in Chriſt for; and be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that Chriſt came for that very end, that thou mighteſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain through him a rich ſupply of all thy wants; and if you ſin, as who lives and ſins not? make it your firſt and greateſt work, to baſten to the blood of ſprinkling; and reſt by faith upon the Lord Jeſus for a pardon, and beſure to let a renewed act af faith lead thee to repentance. I do not ſay but it is a duty to repent, and to get godly ſorrow, and ſhame, and holy reſolutions to wait on Chriſt for ſtrength to walk better; but if you would do theſe duties in ſincerity, and with acceptation, let faith be the firſt of them; and if the divel ſhould ſo far prevail with any of you at any time, as to draw you into the ſnare of fin ſo far, as that you ſhould queſtion your ſincerity; or if you ſhould ſee juſt cauſe ſo to do, yet be ſure you do not caſt away your confidence, but if the divel or your own conſciences, do lay more to your charge this way, then you do well know how to anſwer; yet be ſure at leaſt, that as ungodly loſt ſinners you caſt your ſelves upon the free grace of God, in the blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Thirdly and laſtly, here is a word for ſuch as have heard the glad tidings of ſalvation ſounding in your eares, but unto this very day, have not ſubmitted unto the Lord Jeſus, and are as farr from having made your calling and election ſure, as if the Goſpel had never ſounded in your eares; nay I fear, you know as little of God and of Chriſt, and of the ends of his coming, as thoſe that have had no ſuch means to know him at all; but if you do know him, yet if you have not given up your ſelves unto him, neither yet are waſhed nor ſanctified, but do ſtill remain in your naturall filth, and as farr from regeneration as ever; your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is far worſe, then thoſe that never heard of the name of God, except you repent and amend in time: Now therefore I
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118935:33"/>beſeech you once more, before it be too late, do not poſt off your return to God, nor refuſe to lay hold upon thoſe ſweet offers of grace, that have been made unto you ſo often. Oh conſider, when you come to die, how little pleaſure you will have in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring all the vain pleaſures, for which you neglected your own ſalvation; or what profit you will have at that day, in all thoſe profits that have ſtollen your hearts from Jeſus Chriſt. Oh conſider, how it will wound your hearts, to think that you were often told, what a Saviour Chriſt would be unto you, if ſo be that you would but come unto him, and how often you were invited, and intreated in his name to come unto him, &amp; the ſweet promiſes that are made in the Goſpel laid before you, but you unkindly, and unthankfully refuſed them, and choſe rather the vain pleaſures and profits of the world, and of ſin, then the juſtifying, and ſanctifying grace of Chriſt. Oh when a ſoul ſhall remember what promiſes of pardon, and grace of help againſt ſin, and deliverance out of the ſnares of the devil, he might and ſhould have had, if he had come to Chriſt, and he lovingly intreated to accept of thoſe offers, but hath neglected and refuſed them till it is too late; how muſt this needs wound his ſoul? Oh that this that I now ſay, would prevail with any of you, yet to come to Chriſt that you may have life; but if it will not, remember at the great day, that you had a ſufficient warning; and this much I ſhall leave to your conſideration, and to the bleſſing of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="exercise">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:118935:34"/>
               <head>THE EIGHTH EXERCISE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 17.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true God.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>I ſhall now come to ſpeak a word to that which I had thought wholly to have omitted, by reaſon I ſpake to the ſame thing in the words immediately going before; but for the Readers fake I ſhall bring up that in the rear, which ſhould have been in the front, if I had had the leaſt thought of writing; and for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this word eternal life, you are to know, that it is called ſo by reaſon of that oppoſition it hath with that ſtate of death and miſery, in which the ungodly ſuffer eternall torments; that is called death by reaſon of the woe and ſorrow that muſt for ever be indured; and this is called life by reaſon of that happineſs and comfort that ſhall eternally be enjoyed. Obſerve then, that this word eternal life ſets forth unto us the bleſſedneſs of that eternal glory which the ſaints ſhall for ever enjoy hereafter in the preſence of the Lord, as you have it, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſet ſomething of that happineſs before you, and for that end I pray you take notice, that eye hath not ſeen, nor eare heard, neither hath it entered into the heart of man to conceive, how exceeding glorious that eſtate is, which the Lord hath prepared for thoſe that truly beleeve; but although it is impoſſible to ſet forth the glory of it, as <hi>Pauls</hi> words do clearly imply, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3, 4. yet the Scriptures do ſpeak very much of the glory of it, although it may be when a ſoul ſhall come to ſee it, he will ſay the one half was never told him.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, conſider what <hi>David</hi> ſaith of it, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 16.11, <hi>Thou wilt ſhew me the path of life, in thy preſence is fulneſs of joy, at thy right hand there are pleaſures for evermore.</hi> You ſee whither the path of life will lead a man; it goeth directly into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:118935:34"/>of God, and there is <hi>fulneſs of joy,</hi> ſaith the Prophet; mark it, that is a full word indeed to expreſs the fulneſs of a mans happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Oh the bleſſedneſs of a man that knows God and Jeſus Chriſt, and walks up to that knowledg; he ſhall have fulneſs of joy. Firſt he ſhall have nothing to hinder his joy; but all ſickneſs ſorrow, griefe, and troubles, of all kinds ſhall be removed, a man ſhall have never an ill neighbour there to vex him, nor any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that ſhall ſpeak a word to grieve him, but all his companions ſhall be holy and ſpiritual, ſuch as will perfectly love God, and love him, and rejoice in his happineſs with perfect joy, there be ſhall never ſee nor hear either perſon or thing that ſhall miniſter the leaſt diſcomfort or trouble to him, none that will backbite, or ſpeak kinder then his heart thinketh, will ever be found in that place, no divel ſhall come there to tempt, nor ſnare to turn the heart aſide from God; but there ſhall be perfect freedom from all manner of moleſtation whatſoever; and contrarily, there ſhall be the fulneſs of all joy and peace, holineſs and love; there ſhall be no want of any comfort, no nor of any degree of comfort that the heart of man can poſſibly deſire. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes of a <hi>joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable and full of glory,</hi> that beleevers meet withal here, 1 Pet. 1.8. and <hi>Paul</hi> calls that fame <hi>ſealing teſtimony of the Spirit, the earneſt of our inheritance, Ephoſ.</hi> 1.13, 14. now if the Lord do give ſuch taſtes of the cup of conſolation in this life to ſome poor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, as thoſe texts do plainly intimate he doth; what then may we think their portion ſhall be when they ſhall come home to their inheritance? I ſhall give you an inſtance in one poor ſoul that I knew, who being in anguiſh of ſpirit for ſome two years together, and having ſought the Lord with ſorrow and tears many a time, at laſt being in the fields in the night weeping and praying, it pleaſed the Lord to manifeſt his love wonderfully, and by his ſpirit to open the ſweet promiſes of the Goſpel and to ſeal up his love in the promiſes with that clearneſs of aſſurance and exceeding joy, that untill that time that ſoul could never think that heaven it ſelf would have yeelded that fulneſs of joy and conſolation; but doubtleſſe that ſoul never yet, nor any other that is this day on earth, ever taſted more then an earneſt penny of the fulneſs of that glory that ſhall be injoyed in the life to come.</p>
               <p>Another note in the text obſervable, is this; that theſe pleaſures
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:118935:35"/>are to be injoyed at the right hand of God; which plainly inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates thus much unto us. That the Lord will put forth his wiſdome mercy, and all ſufficiency in the glorifying of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ſhall be accounted worthy of that kindome, for ſo much the right hand ſignifieth, for there you know, the ſtrength lieth, and there we uſe to ſet the perſons we highly favour, and would put the greateſt honour upon that we know how. There is one thing more in this text worth noting, and that is this word, for evermore; that is it, that exceedingly adds to the fulneſs of this glory, that it is of an everlaſting continuance? ſo that as there ſhall be a freedome from all ſin, ſnare, temptation, trouble, or whatſoever might produce complaint, or cauſe any degree of ſorrow; and likewiſe an injoyment of all thoſe comforts that the heart of man can poſſibly wiſh or deſire. So alſo, there ſhall be no fear no nor ground of fear, that ever this bleſſed eſtate ſhall change or fade, but remain ſure and durable to all eternity. Oh conſider of the worth and glory of this happy condition! when the ſouls company and injoyments ſhall both be perfect. Another text that I would pray you to mind, is in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49. the words are theſe; <hi>and as we have born the Image of the earthy, we ſhall alſo bear the Image of the heavenly.</hi> Indeed if it were not for that which lies in this promiſe, all the reſt of a mans injoyments could not be ſo exceeding comfortable unto him for what would it be to a man to ſee all his company, holy and ſpiritual, full of love, joy, and peace, being free from all the ſtain and appearance of evil? if he himſelf ſhould be corrupt and remain ſtill burthened with the ſame degrees of ſin, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectneſs to tranſgreſſion, as I fear the beſt of Saints do find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves inclined and ſubject to, while they are here. But this ſhall be the great happineſs of the Saints, that after the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they ſhall be made fully conformable to their heavenly condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and company, bearing the Image of Chriſt as they have born old <hi>Adams</hi> image, that is, they ſhall bear it as truly and as fully, being made as like him as ever they were like <hi>Adam.</hi> Now it is evident unto us all, how like <hi>Adam</hi> we have been, having all thoſe luſts in our hearts that ever were in his; having as little delight in God and deſire of heaven, and being as barren and deſtitude of all ſpiritual grace as he; but then we ſhall be made fully like our Lord Jeſus, as free from all carnallity, errour, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:118935:35"/>ſin, as he is; and as heavenly minded, ſpiritual, and as full of love to God, and to holyneſs as he; elſe alaſs if a poor ſoul ſhould go clog'd and fettered into heaven with ſuch a degree of corruption as he carrieth about with him here, his condition would be very uncomfortable; for if he ſhould come into the preſence of a holy God, the holy Angels, and Saints, made perfect; and in all this heavenly company ſhould not ſee one ſoul but ſuch as are perfect in love and holyneſs, but he himſelf unlike them, corrupt and ſinful; it could not chuſe but break his heart; but now this ſhall be the great conſolation of all the ſaints; that as their injoyments ſociety, and condition is in all reſpects, holy, happy, and perfect, ſo alſo ſhall their hearts be; there ſhall be no degree of blindneſs in the underſtanding at that day; but the judgment will be able to ſee the worth of Chriſt, of grace, of holyneſs, and of all that happineſs, which it doth injoy, eſteeming of it according to the riches of its worth and glory, the affections will be perfectly ſet upon the love of God and his people, and that holy and heavenly condition in which they are, ſhall be perfect ſatisfaction to them, their wils ſhall be perfectly conformed to the will of God, and not the leaſt dreg or ſtain of ſin ſhall be left in the whole ſoul; No luſt ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the eye, nor in the eare, nor in any of the members in the leaſt degree; but the whole man ſhall be made meet to injoy communion with the Lord, and an inheritance among all them that are ſanctified; and for their bodies the ſcriptures tels us, that they ſhall be like the Lord Jeſus Chriſts own moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body, ſhining as the ſon in the kingdome of their father. Oh conſider of the ſixeetneſs of this heavenly eſtate, how full of comfort it is, when a poor ſoul that in this life it may be, did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee a good day, but hath been tormented with hateful luſts and ſtrange temptations, and oppreſſed with many and great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſhall be taken into a condition of freedome from all pain, ſickneſs, trouble, fear, temptation, ſin, where he ſhall hunger no more, nor thirſt no more, where there is no tears nor any perſon or thing that can for ever offend or greive him: And alſo on the other hand, is come to injoy as much peace, joy, love, and comfort, and whatſoever the heart can wiſh or deſire in all fulneſs, and is paſt the fear and danger of loſeing theſe comforts, or any degree of them for ever, but is ſure to injoy them to all
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:118935:36"/>eternity: how full I ſay of conſolation will ſuch a ſoul be? I pray you let us think of it, and make ſome due improvement of this precious truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. And in the firſt place, if it be ſo that their is ſuch a bleſſed condition, prepared for poor beleevers, that is ſo exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing excellent and glorious; then let your hearts be ſet upon it, and do not ſuffer the vanities of this preſent life to ſteal away the heart from this moſt glorious and eternal inheritance. Beloved it becomes you to be heavenly minded, you will get a great deal of advantage by it, it will marvellouſly ſtrengthen you in the way of obedience, and of ſufferings; you have two clear exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſet before you by the author to the <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.24, 25, 26. there the Spirit of God tels us by what means <hi>Moſes</hi> became ſo able to forſake the glory of this world, and to chuſe afflictions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people of God; 'tis there manifeſted to be through the exerciſe of faith upon that glorious reward, that he had reſpect unto; and in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12, 2 there we have an exhortation to follow the example of our Lord, &amp; to take the ſame courſe that he did to hold out in a way of obedience and ſufferings, and that the author there tels us, was by looking unto the joy that was ſet before him; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray you let us follow theſe bleſſed patterns that have gone before us, &amp; let us tread in their ſteps, if we mean to come to the ſame place where they now are. Beloved, if the Lord Jeſus himſelf &amp; his ſervant <hi>Moſes</hi> had need of this cordial to ſtrenthen them to the doing and ſuffering of what they were to do, &amp; to meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in this life; how much more had we need to uſe the ſame means? therefore let your hearts be ſet upon this heavenly inheritance, and to that end, that your affections may be raiſed to mind and to deſire the things that are above: I pray you get as clear a ſight as poſſibly you can of the glory of that rich inheritance: now although you cannot ſee this glory with theſe bodily eyes; yet ſaith can ſee within the vail, and can make abſent things preſent; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet that to work to conſider of the glorious diſcriptions the Scriptures give of this crown of glory; thoſe texts that have been named already will much help you herein, and many others I might name; <hi>Peter</hi> tels us that in conſideration of the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joy we ſhall partake of, when the glory of Chriſt ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, there is cauſe of rejoycing now, even when we are under fiery trials; and ſo we ſee in the caſe of <hi>Paul</hi> and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:118935:36"/>
                  <hi>Silas, Acts</hi> 16.24, 25. that when one might expect to have found them weeping for ſorrow of heart, by reaſon of thoſe bitter afflictions that they then lay under; then were they ſinging for joy of heart by reaſon of that glorious hope they had by faith a ſight of; which hope <hi>Paul</hi> in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. <hi>calls an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and eternal weight of glory.</hi> I pray you meditate upon theſe texts, and ſuch like, as you may find many in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that you may have your hearts affected with this heavenly condition; and if you would ſee the glory of this condition and be affected with it, then keep the heart and life as clean from all manner of ſin, as it is paſſible likewiſe; for ſin is of a blinding, as well as of a heardening nature; and if you let out your hearts unto it, it will ſurely corrupt the ſoul, and hinder and diſable it, that it cannot relliſh thoſe things that are of a heavenly nature; therefore take heed of ſin, and of all the means that lead to it, for if once you give up your ſelves unto any ſin, it will ſo blind and alienate the heart from God, and from heavenly things, that you will not be capable to be wonne by the promiſes of eternal life, neither will you ſee a beauty in them; and as it is with ſin, ſo is it likewiſe with the things of this world; if the heart be ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, they will ſteal it away from the things that be above; therefore take heed that you let not out your hearts too freely to the moſt lawful pleaſures and profits that be; for if you do ſurfeit upon them, they will keep out the love and deſire of eternal life, and hinder you from walking in the path that leades unto it, and ſo deprive you of it, as unavoidably as ſin it ſelf can do it; and as you are to avoid theſe evils on the one hand, ſo on the other, it will be meet to wait on the Lord Jeſus for the ſweet taſtes of his love, the which when you have once experience of, you wil by that earneſt penny know ſomething of the riches &amp; worth of eternal life; now for that end I beſeech you wait attentively, for the Lord in the uſe of al his Ordinances, for there he wil be found, in them, in the aſſemblies of his people you may expect to find him, becauſe it is his walk: but take notice I pray you, that a negligent formal overtly uſe of them, I do not call for, but be ſure you make it your buſineſs to look for him, and to injoy communion with him, and <hi>to taſt and ſee,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 348. <hi>how good the Lord is:</hi> if you look for him with that intention and deſire as the Church did, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.8. you will be ſure to find him, he will not long hide himſelf from ſuch a ſoul; but among all other duties I could
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:118935:37"/>wiſh that you would watch to meet with him alone, and there open your hearts to him freely, and tell him the very worſt you know by your ſelves, and that with an intent and an indeavour to ſhame and humble your ſelves before him; and be you aſſured that he will exalt you in due time; let him know what you would have, and be ſure to follow him dayly: conſider what counſel he gives you himſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Luke</hi> 11. from the 5. to 14. &amp; the 18. the 8 firſt verſes; and if you follow this counſel you may be ſure that the Lord will graciouſly open his heart unto you at laſt, and give you ſuch a taſte of the water of life, that will ſet your ſouls a longing for your fill thereof and that wil make you both do and ſuffer for Chriſt with much chearfulneſs, and willingneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. The ſecond uſe is this; if it be ſo, that there is ſo rich a portion attainable as eternal life; then be ſure to take a ſpeedy courſe for the getting a clear aſſurance of your own intereſt in that happy injoyment, do not trifle your time away any longer, but ſet upon the work without delay; and to that end that you may make ſure work; obſerve the counſel of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> in his ſecond Epiſtle, 1.5. to the 12, you ſhall find two things minded by <hi>Peter</hi> in this text, in order to the getting of a full aſſurance.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe, is to lay the foundation of Chriſtianity in true beleeving; that is clear in theſe words; <hi>Add to your faith vertue;</hi> implying that faith muſt needs be there, for it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ad vertue to it elſe. Now therefore in the firſt place although you be never ſo impenitent and wicked, yet reſt upon the grace of God in Chriſt, yea if you think alſo that you have attained ſome vertue, patience, or love, or other fruits of the Spirit; yet do not as Saints but as ſinnets, reſt upon the blood of Chriſt; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I pray you, that neither works done, nor grace receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is to be reſted on for Juſtification; but we are juſtified in and through beleeving, and reſting upon the blood of Chriſt, who freely juſtifieth men as they are ſinners, &amp; ungodly ones: and therefore note it well, neither their repentance nor love, but <hi>faith, is imputed for righteouſneſs;</hi> look <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>And by faith are we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſons of God, Galat.</hi> 3.26. I do not ſay, but there are ſome promiſes made to the ſaints, as they are ſaints, ſuch as are in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.10.17, 19 &amp; many other like there be; and with theſe the godly may comfort themſelves, and none but thoſe that are ſaints can claim an intereſt in them: yet notwithſtanding, that tranſlating
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:118935:37"/>act, as I may ſo call it, in and through which, a man is made of a child of wrath, a child of light; I ſay again, that thing or means that maketh him a Son of God, that was none before, is this act of beleeving and reſting on the blood of Chriſt, as a man conſidereth himſelf a ſinner and ungodly, without the leaſt degree of worth in himſelf; and as a beleever reſteth on the blood of Chriſt for juſtification, ſo likewiſe he expecteth from the free grace of God, in and through the ſame blood ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, glory, outward things, and in a word, all things appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to life and godlyneſs; for true faith deſireth and reſteth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord for the accompliſhment of all the promiſes that he hath made, as well as for any of them.</p>
               <p>The ſecond means that <hi>Peter</hi> directs us to uſe, for the getting aſſurance of eternal life, is, to <hi>add to our faith vertue, knowledg, temperance, patience, godlineſs, brotherly kindneſs, and charity;</hi> under which heads are concluded all the graces and fruits of the Spirit of Chriſt; theſe ſaith he, you muſt add to your faith, theſe you muſt abound in: and as it is in the 3 <hi>chap.</hi> and laſt <hi>verſe, grow in;</hi> and then if you grow in grace, and perſevere in well-doing, and abound therein more and more, you ſhall ſaith he, <hi>never fall, but have an abundant enterance, into the everlaſting kingdom of our Lord and Saviour,</hi> ver. 10 11. As if he ſhould ſay, by this means you ſhall be able, to keep and injoy a clear and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant aſſurance of eternall life; and this is to be done by <hi>giving dilligence, ver.</hi> 10. I pray you obſerve it my brethren, dilligence muſt be uſed, it is not a lazy formal profeſſion, and an overly careleſs performance of duties, that will either give, or keep aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of ſalvation; a man muſt be ready to open to the ſpirit, when he knocketh, and to hearken to his motions, and take heed of rebelling againſt him, and labour to avoid all thoſe unworthy courſes, that tend to grieve and to quench the ſpirit; and if you thus do you may be aſſured, the ſpirit will not fail to do his office, but he will give unto, and maintain in the ſoul aſſurance of eternal life, and that will be a moſt ſweet injoyment, the man that hath it may want friends, riches health, and outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments, but he cannot want comfort, joy, and peace; his ſoul ſhall be full of conſolation, however the world goes with him, or againſt him, and he ſhall be able in the worſt of times, to ſay, that both life and death, ſhall be to him advantage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. And in the laſt place, this may ſerve to reprove the folly
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:118935:38"/>of all thoſe, that ſpend all their time and ſtrength, in the purſuit of the things of this preſent life, with the neglect of the life that is eternal; and therefore, well might <hi>Solomon</hi> term wicked men fools, for indeed their courſes are madneſs, and folly; and indeed there is no folly to be compared to this, of running after the trifles and empty vanities of this world, and the letting of the golden op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertunities ſlip, in which you ſhould make ſure eternal life. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved; the moſt lawful, and the moſt excellent injoyments, that you can meet withall under the ſun, what are they but very husks, and doggs-meat? nay droſſe and dung, in compariſon of that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal inheritance, which is ſurely kept, for all them, that love the appearing of our Lord Jeſus. Think of it I pray you, and be not ſo wilfully fooliſh, and mad, as to loſe this bleſſed and rich portion, for any preſent pleaſures or profits whatſoever; although they may ſeem never ſo ſweet: if you ſhould ſee a man in the time when his harveſt is ripe, run up and down to catch butter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flies, or go every day to the woods a nutting, till his corn were loft; would you not think this man to be worſe then a fool? beloved ſo fooliſh, yea ten thouſand times more fooliſh, is that man that ſhall gain the whole world, and all the glory of it with the loſſe of eternall life; now therefore once more I beſeech you, as you love your own poor ſouls, mind what I have ſaid unto you. Beloved, your own happineſs and comfort, only is concerned in it, as for the Lord you cannot hurt him, neither will he loſe any glory, although you ſhould be eternally condemned and pariſh: and as for me althovgh I ſhould be glad, and exceedingly rejoice that you might reap the fruit and comfort of all my labours, and that upon this account, we might all rejoice together in the day of Chriſt; yet if you do not, but fooliſhly and wickedly forſake your own mercies; I pray you take notice, that I know the loſſe will be your own, and I ſhall receive my reward according to my labour, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8. whether you profit by it or no; and <hi>although Iſrael be not gathered, yet ſhall I be glorious in the eyes of the Lord,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 49.5. Now therefore conſider, that your own eternal welfare meerly is concerned in it; and if that which I have ſaid, will not prevail with you, I cannot help it. I ſhall to this text ſpeak no more, but commend you and what I have ſaid unto you, unto him that is able to bleſſe you, and that alſo delighteth to pour down bleſſings.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="signs">
            <pb facs="tcp:118935:38"/>
            <head>Signes of a Dying Chriſtian.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> I. WHen you are ſo indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to aſſemble, that you can come, or you cannot come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> II. When in your pureſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip you are quickly weary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> III. When you care not to hear one matter often, though ſutable truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> IV. When few Sermons will pleaſe you, either you like not matter, or manner, or man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> V. When you think that you know enough; you may think hat you know enough upon theſe deceivable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts.</p>
            <p n="1">1 When you meaſure what you know by your own oyes or light, you think that you know enough, not meaſuring what you know by the rule of Knowledge, the word of God. 2 When you meaſure what you know, by what once you did know; not conſidering that further light forceth further knowledg, &amp; cals for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable practiſe. 3 When you mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure what you know, by what you ſee others that profeſs to know, do what they do. 4 When you meaſure what you know, by what you are diſpoſed to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice or do, picking or chooſing ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God as like you. 5 When you meaſure not what you know, by what God in his word calls you to do.</p>
            <p>Signs how you may know you are clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with this ſpirit of Deceit.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When you have a low value of that meanes, that under God firſt brought you to know. 2. When you are mighty prodigall of what you know, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no matter well managed, that you have not moſt voice in. 3 When you pleaſe your ſelves with the thought, that few or none outſtrip you in knowledg, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a ſecret ſcorn to compare your ſelves with any. 4 When in all things materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, you are not careful to take counſel of God, before you bring matters to action.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> VI. When a ſmal offence will keep you from Chriſts Table.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> VII. When you have no great mind to prayer, in which there is neceſſity and excellency; lets &amp; helps. Neceſſity 1. from Command; 2 From the Example; 3 The Proviſion; 4 The importunity; 5 The Danger; 6 the Advantage. Its Excellency: Firſt it engageth Gods ſtrength; 2 It holdeth with holy reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Gods hands; 3 It makes every condition ſavory or ſweet; 4 In no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition we can be barr'd from it.</p>
            <p>Letts: 1 Wandring thoughts; 2 Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in an unreverent adventuring before the Lord; 3 Boſom fin or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant delight in ſome ſecret Luſt; 4 VVant of reconciliation to Brethren; 5 Deſpairing doubts of being anſwer'd.</p>
            <p>Helps to Prayer; for ſay ſome, I would, but I cannot Pray, I want words when I go to my Knees, all I can do is but to ſigh.</p>
            <p n="1">1 From the neceſſity and excellency of Prayer; labour to get a feeling of the neceſſity and excellency, ſo as that thy heart goeth under a grievous burden, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou canſt not pray. 2 Study much to be ſenſible of your great want of Gods daily help. 3 Conſider God hath provided no way for you to acqualnt him with your wants, but Prayer; and if you cannot pray, how will you make, your Complaints to God? 4 Conſider that all your mercies become bleſſings to you no other way but through Prayer. 5 Conſider what a miſerable condition wil yours be if caſt into the Lyons Den, VVhales Belly, or the Stocks 6 Intreat Jeſus Chriſt to teach you to Pray.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118935:39"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Signe</hi> VIII. VVhen you have no great delight in reading the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; ignorance whereof brings theſe ſix Calamities.</p>
            <p n="1">1 It makes you in a wilderneſs when ſickneſs and affliction comes, becauſe you will not know how, and why they come. 2 Ignorant that your uneven walking with God, may bring upon your ſelves death before its time. 3 Ignorant how to ask in Faith the things you want for ſoul or body. 4 Ignorant wherein you may prevent the preſence and comforts of Gods Holy Spirit. 5 Ignorant that there is a Legion of evil Spirits waiting hourly to take advantage againſt you. 6 Ignorant that you may hinder Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit from doing any effectual work upon your ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> IX. VVhen you are mighty inquiſitive after novelties rather than wholſome Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> X. VVhen you can hear of foul miſcarriages in others, with little or no heart remorſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> II. VVhen in your comings together, your talk is not ſavory and Heavenly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XII. VVhen you are ſo little prepared for the ſolemn Aſſemblies, as that they come before you think of them, or long for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XIII. When you come to the Aſſembly more for fear of Brethrens eye, than Chriſts eye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XIV. VVhen the decay in Chriſts houſe leſs troubles you than the decay in your own houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XV. VVhen you can ſee Chriſts Children ſtoop with trouble; and you not ſympathize with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XVI. VVhen you will rather betray the Name of Jeſus, and the credit of his Goſpel by your ſilence, than appear for it to your own ſuffering and diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XVII. VVhen at a ſmal of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence you are ſo impatient that you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit great ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XVIII. VVhen you are more careful to get the words of Chriſts people, than the Spirit of Chriſts people, the form than the power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XIX. VVhen you are not much troubled at your own miſcarriages, while they are kept from publick view.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XX. VVhen you love leaſt thoſe Brethren that deal moſt faithfully with you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XXI. VVhen under more than ordinary troubles, you are not more than ordinary in Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XXII. VVhen you are mighty careleſs to enquire after the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual cauſe of affliction, and mighty care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to enquire after the natural cure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XXIII. VVhen you pray more for afflictions being removed, than ſanctified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XXIV. VVhen under Gods calamity, you can neither find neceſſity nor excellency to humble your ſelves by faſting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XXV. VVhen Gods Rod worketh ſo little upon your hearts, that you can neither tell wherefore its come, nor what good it hath done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XXVI. VVhen you have an evil eye to your fellow Brethren, becauſe they outgrow you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XXVII. When the thoughts of your deareſt Luſt, or any ſin is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XXVIII. When you are mighty curious about the leſſer matters of Gods Law; but mighty careleſs about the weightier.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signe</hi> XXIX When the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits help to the great work of Mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeems not of abſolute need to you.</p>
            <p>XXX. When you are ſo ignorant of your ſpiritual ſtanding, that you know not whether you grow or decay.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
